<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Paules Crosse, the second of Nouember. 1606. By Richard Stocke, preacher of Al-hallowes, Bread-streete, London</title>
            <author>Stock, Richard, 1569?-1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 134 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12983</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23276</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117808</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853018</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853018</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18377</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12983)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18377)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1365:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Paules Crosse, the second of Nouember. 1606. By Richard Stocke, preacher of Al-hallowes, Bread-streete, London</title>
                  <author>Stock, Richard, 1569?-1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 75, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] C[reede] for Edmond Weauer, and William Welby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>With a preliminary errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded and show-thorough.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18377:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18377:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT Paules Croſſe, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of Nouember. 1606.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Richard Stocke, <hi>Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of Al-hallowes,</hi> Bread-ſtreete, <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by T. C. for Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond Weauer, and William Welby. 1609.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18377:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18377:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father in God, <hi>Iames,</hi> by Gods prouidence, Lord Biſhop of <hi>Bathe,</hi> and <hi>Welles,</hi> R. S. <hi>wiſheth all Grace, true Honor, and Comforts in this life, and the Crowne of glory, in the life to come.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ighte Reuerende in CHRIST,<note place="margin">Saluia: Maſſil. de guber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. Dei.</note> the anger of God, &amp; his fearefull pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments (for <hi>Iradiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis est poena peccantis</hi>) hath bene heauie vpon vs for the ſpace of theſe almoſt ſixe yeares. The cauſe doubtleſſe is the ſinnes of the time, which haue defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Land, and prouoked God to ſend ſuch plagues as may purge the land of vs, when we will not purge it, and our ſelues from our ſinnes. Which ſinnes, what they are, as I haue touched diuers in the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon following, ſo none ſeemeth to mee
<pb facs="tcp:18377:3"/>to be more offenſiue to the eyes of God, then that popiſh Idolatrie which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the land, wherewith euerie place, countrie and Citie is horriblie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed; though as the prophet ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 8.12.</note> 
               <hi>it is but in the darke, and in the chamber of their</hi> imagery. Which was an occaſion to me, beeing called to the ſtage of the land, to act this part I haue done in this Sermon: namely, to perſwade euerie man to iudge himſelfe; and them, to whom the ſword of iuſtice is committed, to iudge other malefactors, ſpecially Romiſh Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, and to execute the iuſt lawes vpon them; becauſe God will not iudge when man doth iudge before: as the Iudges of aſſile will not cenſure againe thoſe male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors, whom the Iuſtices of the ſeſſions haue formerly puniſhed. But when this is neglected, God will, and can not, for his iuſtice, but he muſt bring this &amp; the like fearefull iudgementes vpon the land. Which as they were the occaſion of my preaching of this doctrine, ſo they are ſome cauſes of my publiſhing of it in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: to trie if I might by any meanes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke euery man in his ſeuerall place and
<pb facs="tcp:18377:3"/>condition to this preuenting courſe of Gods iudgementes; At the leaſt, I ſhall haue my owne diſcharge by it. Now I haue preſumed to bring it forth into pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like vnder your name and countenaunce for diuerſe both publike, and priuate rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and reſpectes: Publike, firſt you are now aduanced to a ſpeciall place of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment in the Church, and haue that authoritie in your hands, that you may cauſe &amp; effect great reformation of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and redreſſe of many things, which are highly diſpleaſing to God. To which if I might be any occaſion to excite your Lordſhip, I ſhould thinke I had effected ſome great good: becauſe your example, as it might prouoke others in authoritie, both in Church and common wealth to do the like; ſo it might animate them to goe forward, with hope it would be well accepted of his highnes, when they ſhall ſee you, (who haue beene ſo continually in his preſence, and ſo daily conuerſant with him, and can not but knowe his heart &amp; affection) take ſome round and conſtant courſes in reforming of abuſes both in manners and doctrine.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18377:4"/>
            <p>Secondly, your place you yet enioy ſo nigh vnto his Maieſties perſon; whereby you haue done hitherto good offices to the Church,<note place="margin">The Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Popes Breeues, &amp; Bellar. Letter.</note> (her enemies being witnes) in iuſtly and wiſely exaſperating his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties heart againſt theſe foxes, who would deſtroy her vines. Now if I might bee anie meanes to further your willing minde to be conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in this dutie, I ſhould iudge it in me a good ſeruice to the Church, as in your ſelfe it will be a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſeruice to the King of Kings; honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to his highnes, profitable to the Church, comfortable to all her friendes, and bring you great honour from God and good men. Which pointe I will not here much preſſe in the particular, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I haue in the treatiſe following don it in the generall; though to vſe <hi>Bernards</hi> words in another caſe,<note place="margin">De dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do Deo.</note> 
               <hi>Non prout dignum rei, ſed prout datum mihi.</hi> Yet let me intreat your Lordſhip, or rather adiure you by that honour and ſauour which God hath giuen you with your Soueraigne, and by that account you muſt giue for the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of it, before the great King in that great day, that you would goe on in
<pb facs="tcp:18377:4"/>this ſo religious and profitable a worke, namely, to excite his Maieſtie to wake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ſleeping lawes, that as he hath long ſung mercie, he would at length tune iuſtice; and command indeed that his lawes may haue their courſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.8.</note> 
               <hi>that betimes he would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the wicked of the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; that ſuch workers of iniquitie may be cut off from the citie of the Lord.</hi> It is not vnfitting your Lo. (beei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ng called to be a reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Biſhop, a gouernor of the Church) to incite him to this, ſince it was <hi>the conſecrating of the Leuites hands to the Lord, for euery man to ſlay his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.29.27.</note> 
               <hi>his companion, and his neighbour,</hi> who had defiled the land with Idolatrie. And it is no leſſe then neceſsitie requireth of his Maieſtie, both for the good of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,<note place="margin">Thomas Worthing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonus preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter.</note> his poſteritie (thoſe hopefull plants) his whole people, and the church of God. Sith they boaſt not at home onely, but a broad, of the great increaſe of this Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous broode amongſt vs. There is one who hath lately publiſhed two Tomes of <hi>Bristowes</hi> the Ieſuite, written in Latine, called <hi>Motiua Anti-haretica,</hi> who in his Epiſtle Dedicatorie, ſpeaks thus; <hi>Poſt diu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnas in Anglia ingraueſcentes, pro fide Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholica,
<pb facs="tcp:18377:5"/>perſecutiones, ita plus ſolito creſcat Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tholicorum ibi mumerus, ac zelus, vt ſpes ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulgeat (Diuina praestante miſericordia) totum illud ampliſsimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Regnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ad ſanctaematris Ec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cleſiae gremiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> breuirediturum.</hi> Is it not then more then need &amp; high time, that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties former lenitie ſhuld be turned into iuſt ſeueritie? leſt he may ſeeme to ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ages to forget both his God &amp; him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, his poſteritie, &amp; people. Which may eaſily be preuented, if his lawes may be at length with ſome rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dnes executed, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially againſt the ſeedes men of treaſon &amp; idolatrie, by whom this popiſh ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is nouriſhed &amp; increaſed in this land. For ſo ſaith the former authour in the ſame place, commending the founders and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders of their Seminaries, as the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of thoſe waters which haue watered theſe weeds till they be fit for the fire, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that <hi>His enim in collegijs Sacerdotes ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiati, &amp; inde in Anglia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miſsi, tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paruas ibi reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionis reliquias co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeruerunt, tum eaſde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (vt nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c videamus) in immenſum propagarunt.</hi> Theſe then by confeſſion beeing the preſeruers and the increaſers of this Idolatrie among vs, there is no way to preuent the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb facs="tcp:18377:5"/>and increaſe of this, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4+ letters">
                  <desc>••••…</desc>
               </gap>by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap>ing off ſuch at leaſt who husband this Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous worke: leaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhould growe to that, they would haue it, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> more then the wheat; when without great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and diſturbance to the whoſe, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of the Church, they cannot be dealt withall. Now that your Lordſhip hath ſuch an opportunitie to further this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the Lord, <hi>who knoweth whether you are come to ſuch a place for ſuch a purpoſe?</hi> &amp;c whether, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome would haue caſt you out, you haue yet but God bene kept in, to ſuch an end? The ſanour God brought you firſt into, with your Soueraigne, and his vpholding of you in it to greater aduancement, ſeemeth to re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e no leſſe of you. Without which, I ſhould doubt, you can neither performe thankfulneſſe to God, nor faithfulneſſe to his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie.</p>
            <p>Pardon, I beſeeche your Lordſhip, my plainneſſe and boldneſſe; which I excuſe with that of Bernard to Eugenius: <hi>Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do celſitudinem honoris, &amp; è vicino periculum reformido:</hi> and with that of Hieroure to Salvina, <hi>Abſit vt ſiniſtrum quicquam mihi
<pb facs="tcp:18377:6"/>de te ſuſpicari liceat: ſed ex abundantia lubri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam aetate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> (dicerem ego,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 9.</note> lubricum ſtatum &amp; gradum) <hi>monuiſſe, pietatis eſt:</hi> imò amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris non vulgaris.</p>
            <p>Now the priuate reaſons which haue moued me to make choiſe of your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, vnder whoſe name this ſlender la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of mine might appeare in the ſight of men, is your auncient fauour which you bore to wardes mee in the Vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; and that good reſpect, though vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, which you had of mee, for my good and preferment there: as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſince, the renewing of the ſame many wayes towards mee, euen now when you are aduanced to honour and place of dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. So that I could doe noe leſſe then returne a bare &amp; naked ſigne of my good will and heartie affection, for ſo great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours. Now, the Lord of glorie make you faithfull to himſelfe, and your Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, to the Church in generall, &amp; your owne wherof you are made ouerſeer; and that for the furtherance of Gods glorie, the aduauncement of Chriſts holie Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, the comfort of his glorious ſpouſe the Church, the confuſion of the Popes
<pb facs="tcp:18377:6"/>gliſtering <hi>Concubine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nos iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> noſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae Sponſae noſtrae no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letes negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere. Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifac. <hi>8.</hi> de immunit. Eccleſ. c. quoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſexto.</note> the ſeate of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and to the diſcharge of your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in this life, and your account in the great day.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips, in the Lord to be commanded, <hi>Rich. Stocke.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:18377:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18377:7"/>
            <head>¶ To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, thou hast heere from mee a Sermon, as the Sea in a ſtorme hath the Marchants goods, willingly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst my will. When I prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched it, manie were verie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant with mee to print it: but I was then as peremptorie in the denyall, &amp; thought neuer to haue brought it againe into viewe and ſight of men. But the iniquities of the times are ſuch, that ſome men for their gaine care not what preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice and iniurie they doe vnto others. Wherevpon ſome hauing copies of this ſlender labour of myne, though verie imperfect, and of ſome other things of farre greater quantitie in themſelues, and of labour to mee, &amp; thoſe things, whoſe impreſſion would haue coſt them a great ſumme; yet haue gone about to ſeek the allowance of them without my priuitie &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: and had I not had a friend in place, they had at the least obtained an allowance of them, though happely I might haue got knowledge of it, before they had printed much of them.</p>
            <p>Now this thing, being ſhort and ſmall, might hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pely
<pb facs="tcp:18377:8"/>ſome haue paſſed and beene ſpeedily printed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhould haue had notice of it, &amp; that with ſuch imperfections as would haue bene ſmall to my credit, and as little to thy contentment. Wherefore I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued, being importuned by ſome, to ſeeke forth my owne Copie; which in probabilitie is like to haue leſſe imperfections then anie which they had. Which as in ſpeaking, ſo in printing. I purpoſe not to make any pleaſant illurement or inticement, but a remedie &amp; medicine rather, which ſhould not ſo much pleaſe the cares of the idle and curious, as profite the mindes of the ſickely and weake: which if I can compaſſe, I ſhall account it a great fruit of my labours. But if it happen not, I ſhall not thinke I haue laboured in vaine; ſeeing I aſſayed and endeuored to haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited. For happely with men, but certainely with God,<note place="margin">De duplici Martyrio.</note> it is as <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſpeaketh, (if <hi>Cyprian</hi>) <hi>Deus non aeſtimat quenqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ex eventu rerum, ſed ex affectu.</hi> Not the fruit of their labours, but the affection of mens hearts gets them reſpect with God. To whoſe bleſſing I commend thee: and this poore mite, I offer to the treaſurie of the Lordes temple.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine, in Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> Rich. Stocke.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18377:8"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at Pauls Croſſe, the ſeconde of Nouember, 1606.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Eſay. <hi>9 14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Therefore will the Lord cut off from Iſrael, head, and tayle, braunch, and ruſh, in one day.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Eſay. <hi>9 15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The Auncient and the Honourable man, he is the headland the Prophet that teacheth lyes, he is the tayle.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Eſay. <hi>9 16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For the leaders of my people, cauſe them to erre: an I they that are leddely them, are deuoured.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr Sauiour Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares a miniſter <hi>to a ſaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and wiſe Steward,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke. 12.4.</note> whom the Maiſter ſhall <hi>make ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler ouer his houſhould, to giue them their portion of meate, in ſeaſon.</hi> Where are two things approoued: Firſt, his faithfulnes: Secondly, his wiſedome. His faithfulneſſe appeareth in diſpoſing of that he had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18377:9"/>from his maiſter, for his honour, and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilitie, and not for his owne gaine: his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in giuing vnto the houſhould of God their due portion of meate, and that in fit time and ſeaſon, for all meates are not for all perſons, but that which is nouriſhment to ſome, is poyſon to others, neither is that fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at one time which is at another. So fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rech it in Spirituall foode, where many things are ſutable to times of iudgement, which would be vnfit for the day of mercy, and on the contrary. Now I hauing obtained this mercy of God, to bee, though vnworthy, a miniſter and diſpoſer of his myſteries, and by authoritie called to this place: In that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of fidelitie, I haue receiued, I began to thinke what might moſt glorifie God, and in the ſmall degree of wiſedome, God hath giuen me, what portion was fitteſt to Gods houſhold, whereof this auditorie is a part, but eſpecially what was fitteſt for this time, which is as <hi>Hezechiah</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">Iſay 37.3.</note> 
               <hi>A day of tribulation,</hi> and a day of iudgement: I at length reſolued vpon this place and theſe verſes of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſay,</hi> as both ſitting this time and this aſſemblie: out of which I intende not to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther euery thing that may be gathered, as if I would immitate thoſe vvho digge for trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, vvho as <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> ſaith, though they haue taken much riches, yet leaue not till they haue taken all their care being not to take
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18377:9"/>much, but to leaue nothing. But I vvill only chuſe out ſome principall things, vvhich I diſcerne to be of moſt neceſſitie, and profit, ſeeing the length of the text, and the limmit of the time vvill not ſuffer me to run through all.</p>
            <p>The dependaunce of theſe vvords vpon the former, is thus:<note place="margin">Coherence.</note> In this chapter are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained tvvo things: Firſt, comfort and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation to the godly, from the firſt verſe to the eighteenth: Secondly, iudgement and threatnings menaced againſt the vvicked and obſtinate, from the eight verſe to the end, but ſo as before he threatens the rod, he tells them in the eight verſe, that <hi>he had ſent his word vnto Iacob, and it had lighted vpon Iſrael,</hi> and hauing called them by his vvord, and they vvould not be gathered, and hauing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoured to bring them in order, and they vvould not be reformed, then according to that in the prophet, <hi>Heare the rod, and who hath appointed it:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mich. 6 9.</note> In the eleuenth, and tvvelue ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of this chapter, the Prophet threatens a heauie, and grieuous iudgement that God ſhould bring vpon them, an enemie that ſhould deuoure them vvith open mouth, and becauſe they profitted not by that iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he ſaith in the tvvelue verſe; <hi>The wrath of the Lord is not turned away, but his hand is ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out ſtill;</hi> the reaſon of it is giuen in the 13. verſe, and iuſinuated in the 14. verſe, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18377:10"/>the people haue not returned to the Lord that ſinit them, neither doe they ſeeke the Lord of haſtes, therefore he will cut off head, and taile, branch, and ruſh, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Herein vve may obſerue 2. things: 1. the denouncing a Iudgement: 2. the cauſes vvhy the Lord vvould bring it vpon them. In the iudgement are 2. things to be conſidered: 1. the generalitie of it, 2. the impartialitie of it. The generalitie, becauſe the Lord vvil cut off head, and taile. The impartialitie is double: 1. becauſe he vvill as vvell ſmite the head, as the taile; the braunche, as the ruſh; the great, as the ſmall: 2. becauſe hee vvill principallie ſmite the heads, as thoſe that vvere the cauſe of all the corruptions that vvere in the body. The 2. is the cauſes: and they are 2. Firſt, is general, becauſe the people had not profited by former iudgements and leſſe afflictions, therefore they ſhould haue a 2. and 3. vvoe, in the firſt vvord, Therefore:</p>
            <p>The 2. is a particular cauſe in the 16. verſe: becauſe the leaders of the people cauſed them to c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re, and the people vvere content to bee miſled by them, therefore ſhall they bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured all together. So much for the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence and diuiſion of the vvords. And novv for the meaning of the vvords: <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord will cut off, &amp;c.</hi> That is, becauſe the people haue not benefited by the former iudgements, and afflictions to turne to God
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18377:10"/>by repentance, many of them onely ſeeking the Lord by mourning and faſting, and ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, in outward ſhow, which is but as much as hipocrites may doe; but fewe or none of them were ſound to forſake their ſinnes, and turne to God by true repentance, <hi>therfore ſaith the Lord, I wil cut off head, and taile, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The iudgement is, <hi>God will cut off and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy</hi> with a generall iudgement and conſuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the whole ſtate, and the whole land, for this ſinne. For to imagine as ſome do, that the magiſtrate is called here the head, becauſe the head is the ſeate of ſenſe, and beginning of motion; I take it, it is beſides the intent of the Prophet in this place: and that he meerely intendes to note a generall conſaſion and plague that ſhould ſpread ouer the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy from the toppe of the head to the ſole of the foote; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> one ſhould be ſpared. And not onely ſo: but as it is ſaul that his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are generall, ſo they ſhould be without partialitie, God would out off as well the head, as the taile, the weake and feeble ruſh that hangs downe the head, &amp; the ſtronge braunche that is high and mightie, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the 15. verſe hee tells vs whom hee meanes, by head, and whom by taile: <hi>The head is the auncient and honourable, and the taile is the Prophet that teacheth lyes.</hi> Here is another part of Gods impartialitie obſerued: whereas the magiſtrate and the miniſter were the cauſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18377:11"/>of the corruptions and cuill manners of the people, therefore the Lord will ſmite them both, and becauſe theſe too conſpired to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, the magiſtrate deceiued by the falſe Prophets ſlattering, and fauning vpon him, telling him of his inſinite maieſtie, his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute greatneſſe, and power to doe what hee liſt, where he liſt, and puniſh whom he liſt: and being ſo perſwaded by him becauſe of his power, he thinkes any thing is lawfull for him to doe: and on the other ſide, the lying Prophet becauſe he had gotten fauour, and countenance with the magiſtrate, he thought that he ſhould ſettle his neaſt ſo ſure, that he ſhould haue no hurt whatſoeuer came: thus ſaith the Lord, becauſe they haue agreed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, the one to deceiue, and the other to be deceiued; herefore they ſhal be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed both together.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The leaders of my people cauſe them to erre, &amp;c.</hi> Here is the particular reaſon why God would deſtroy them, becauſe there was deceiuers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them and they were willing to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued; as if he ſhould ſay, I ſet miniſters o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer my people, that they ſhould lead them and teach them in the right way, that they ſhould learne knowledge out of the word, and then teach it to others, and teach them what they ought to doe, and reprooue them when they doe that which is not fit, and which they ought not to doe, but on the other ſide
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18377:11"/>they haue ſet their faces, to get the applauſe and liking of the people, preach onely plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and foothing things to pleaſe the care, onely to get fauour and a name, they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haue cauſed the people to erre, and they that were lead by them are willing to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, therefore they ſhall bee deuoured to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: ſo much for the meaning of the words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore will the Lord cut off from Iſrael, &amp;c.</hi> The firſt thing is the generall cauſe of the iudgement that ſhould come vpon this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which was, becauſe they had not ſought the Lord, nor turned to him, nor profited by their former afflictions, <hi>There the Lord would cut them off?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> The firſt thing that wee learne in theſe words is, that this is the dealing of God with an obſtinate and gaine-ſaying people, when they doe not benefite by former and leſſe iudgements that he layes vpon them, to bring heauier, and more fearefull plagues vpon them, this is manifeſt euery-where in the word of God: as <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.<note place="margin">Deut. 28.45</note> Chapter, and in verſe 45. after the Lord had threatened a great many plagues againſt his people: hee ſaith further, that if this ſhould doe them no good: then, <hi>All theſe curſes ſhall come vpon thee and ouertake thee, to deſtroy thee; becauſe thou o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyeſt not the voyce of the Lord thy God.</hi> And in verſe 58. &amp;c. The Lord ſaith, <hi>If thou wilt not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18377:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>obey and doe al the words of this law, that are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in this booke, and feare this glorious and feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full name the Lord thy God, then the Lord will make thy plagues wonderfull, and the plagues of thy ſeede, euen great plagues and of long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: moreouer, he will bring vpon thee, all the diſeaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of Egypt whereof thou waſt afraid; and euery ſickeneſſe, and euery plague, that is written in this booke of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wil the Lord heape vpon thee, till thou bee deſtroyed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Levit. 26.21.22, 23 24.</note> Like to this is that in <hi>Leuiticus</hi> 26. where the Lord ſaith: <hi>If you walke ſtubbornly againſt me, and will not obey me, I will then bring ſeau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n times more plagues vpon you according to your ſinnes; I will ſend wild beaſts vpon you, which ſhall ſpoyle you, and deſtroy your carttell, and make you f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>we in number: yet if by theſe you will not bee reformed by me, but walke ſtubbornely againſt me, then will I alſo walke ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornelie againſt you, and I will ſmite you yet ſeauen times more for your ſinnes.</hi> This alſo made the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> in this chapter to repeate three times theſe words; <hi>For all this, the wrath of the Lord is not turned away, but his hand is ſtretched out ſtill,</hi> as in the 12.17. and 21. verſes. And in the Goſpel our Sauiour Chriſt ſaid to the man that had beene ſicke 38.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 5.14.</note> yeares: <hi>Goe thy way, ſinne no more, leaſt a worſe thing happen vnto thee.</hi> Out of which places, it is apparant that the Lord brings heauier &amp; greater plagues vpon men, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> when they profit not by leſſer. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this is becauſe there is neither equitie
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18377:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>nor right in it, that the Lord ſhould go away, as ouercome with the ſtubbornneſſe, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacie of the people. That were, as if a Prince hauing a rebell ſtanding out againſt him, and beeing norable with a fewe to ſubdue him, ſhould giue ouer, &amp; gather no more forces a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him; which to him were too much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignitie, and diſhonor: So no reaſon the Lord giue ouer his armes til his rebells are brought in.<note place="margin">2. Sam. 20.22.</note> As <hi>Ioah</hi> would not giue ouer his ſiege a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Abell,</hi> till hee had the head of <hi>Sheba</hi> throwne ouer the wall: So the Lord will not giue ouer his ſiedge againſt men, till hee haue the heads of their ſinnes cut off and caſt away. The ſecond reaſon is, that as it is a diſhonour to God, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> ſo it would be daungerous to men, whom he ſhould ſpare: becauſe if that be true in Eccleſiaſtes. 8.11. <hi>Becauſe ſentence is deferred, and not executed ſpeedily, therefore the harts of the children of men are fully ſet to doe euill.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eel. 8.11</note> If deferring of a ſentence doe harden men in their ſins; then much more, if God ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooue his iudgements, and not renew them againe: therefore leſt he ſhould harden them, he will vndoubtedly renew them, that he may reclaime them. Thirdly, the Lord muſt doe it, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> whether he deale with his owne, or with thoſe that are none of his; with his owne to cure them, or the other to deſtroy them: for ſo is the practiſe of Phyſitians and Chirurgians: if they meere with a body harde to worke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18377:13"/>and a ſetled diſeaſe they double the doſes of their medicines, and vſe more violent meanes: So the Lord will deale with his owne when he ſindes them obſtinate: but if they be not his owne, then muſt he doe it, that he may ſhew his power, that hee is able to abate and deſtroy whoſoeuer ſtands out againſt him, for theſe reaſos or the like, it is that the Lord whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he deales with obſtinate men: if leſſe afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons doe them no good, he will bring greater, and heauier plagues vpon them: now hence doe ariſe many ſeuerall godly conſiderations and vſes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> this may make vs to feare; nay, bee aſſured of it, that though God hath for the moſt part freed the land from this deuouring plagues: <hi>Euen from the peſtilence that walketh in the darkneſſe, and the plagues that deſtroyeth at noone day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 91.6.</note> (ſaue that he hath a little returned to this Citie where he begunne, yet are there more heauie and fearefull plagues, and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments at our dores, readie to breake in vpon vs, for this that is here ſaid is true, and as it were ſpoken to vs by <hi>Eſay.</hi> For this is yet the ſtate of the Citie, refractary and obſtinate, as if they had conſpired againſt God, that doe what hee will, they will ſtill bee alwayes the ſame, wicked as they have beene: I (ſpeake generally, for I doubt not but ſome fewe haue well profited by it.)<note place="margin">Hoſea. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord hath had a controuerſie with the inhabitants of this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:18377:13"/>and he hath followed it hard, almoſt for the ſpace of theſe foure yeres. But why did he thus trouble vs, complained he without cauſe? No aſſuredly, <hi>For will a Lyon roare in the forreſt, when he hath no prey?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos. 3.4.</note> For thoſe ſinnes which made him contende with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> haue beene the cauſe of his controuerſie with vs;<note place="margin">Cap. 41.</note> 
               <hi>Hoſea</hi> ſaith, <hi>the Lord had a controuerſie with the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the Land, becauſe there was no truth, nor merey, nor knowledge of God in the land, by ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and lying, and killing, and ſtealing, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, they breake forth, and blood toucheth bloud:</hi> There is no man who dare deny theſe, leaſt he reprooue the Lord, for conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding cauſeleſlie: but ſome will ſay indeede theſe ſinnes were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, but ſince ſo many of vs fell the laſt plague, we are fallen from them. I would to God it were ſo, then might we well hope the controuerſie would end, and that God would remooue his plagues from vs, and renew them no more; but alas who ſeeth not the contrary, when that in <hi>Ieremie</hi> may well be verified of vs, <hi>that the bellowes are burnt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 6.2.29.</note> 
               <hi>the lead is conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and the founder hath melted in vaine, for the wicked are not taken away.</hi> How ſhould we then not feare greater iudgements? But to goe a little further, there are foure ſinnes which brought the iudgements of God vpon <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> firſt, and after vpon <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and made the Lord take away that people at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and ſweepe them away as the duſt of the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18377:14"/>earth; and they were, <hi>Pride, Idleneſſe f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lues of bread, and contempt of the poore:</hi> which ſinnes in this land, and in this Citre haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the cauſe why God hath ſwept away ſo many thouſands of vs. And if theſe ſinnes be ſtill in the land, and not remooued, what hope is there but that there are more fearefull plagues hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ouer our heads? Theſe ſoure ſinnes are the begetters one of another. Pride commonly begetts idlenes: Pride, and Idlenes hegette Fullneſſe of bread, for that is one part of Pride to haue a table richly deckt and furniſhed: and whereas labour would bee ſatisfied with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, yet idleneſſe is a deuourer: now pride, idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and fullneſſe of bread, breede Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the poore: for where theſe are, there can be little reliefe for them. For if the rich man fare deliciouſly euery day, and goe in purple and fine linnen, there will bee hardly any ſcraps left for poore <hi>Lazarus:</hi> ſeeing all is too little to furniſh the table, to pamper the backe, and the belly, for the ſeruice of ſinne and Sathan. Then if this pride be ſpread through the Citie and through the land, what may we expect, but greater plagues to come vpon vs? If any man will put me to prooue it that it is to bee ſound, he ſhall pardon me, I will adde no light to the ſunne; becauſe if a man doe but looke thorow the Citie, in euery place, in euery familie, in euery man, and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, in euery Church and aſſemblie, he ſhall
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18377:14"/>ſee how the pride of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and of <hi>England,</hi> doth teſtifie it to her face. Now to theſe I will adde this ſpeciall one. 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.16.17. where was a ſinne that brought the wrath of God vpon the prople without remedie: which was, that <hi>they miſuſed the meſſengers of God, deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſed the word of God, mocked the Prophets of God, therefore the Lord gaue them into the hands of the Galdeans, who ſlowe their young men with the word, and ſpared neither young man nor virgine, auncient, nor aged.</hi> And are not theſe rhinges thus with vs? were euer the miniſters of God in more contempt? Nay, are they not all in extreame contempt, either juſtly or vniuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie? whether ſuch as doe conforme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues according to the cuſtome of the Church, and will of his maieſtie, or they who refuſe? Whether ſuch as bee glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous or drinkers of wine, and friends of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans &amp; ſinners, as they falſly ſaid of Chriſt, or they be of an honeſter life, and cariage, comming neither cating nor drinking as <hi>Iohn:</hi> whether they be either negligent and idle in their places, and will hardly preach in any ſeaſon but vnſauourly, or they be diligent, and painfull, preaching in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon: whether they be plaine dealing <hi>Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> or ſlattring <hi>Amaziahs:</hi> all are in contempt, ſome of one and ſome of another. Is there the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any remedie, but that heauier wrath muſt come vppon vs, then yet any wee haue felt?
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18377:15"/>
               <hi>Ezech.</hi> 22. When the Lord had reckoned vp many ſinnes which were in that people: <hi>Hee ſaith, I haue ſmitten my hands vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy couetouſnes.</hi> A ſimilitude, from thoſe who incourage dogs to pull downe and deuour, ſhewing with what deſire and earneſtnes, he would contend with them, and bring iudgements vpon them: if ſuch ſinnes be found among vs not leſſoned, but increaſed, ſince the height of our plague, that crueltie and blood bee in our ſtreets, as verſe. 7.8. &amp;c. In thee haue they deſpiſed Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother, in the middeſt of thee haue they oppoſed the ſtrangers: in thee haue they vexed the fatherleſſe, and the widdow. Thou haſt deſpiſed my holy things, and haſt pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my Sabboaths, &amp;c. What can wee expect but the Lord ſhould clappe his hands vpon our couetouſneſſe, and bring a freſh and ſierce reply of ſome fearefull iudgement?</p>
            <p>To conclude this with a ſpeech of <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> in his 5. Homilie to the people of <hi>Antioch:</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Emperours wrath was aſſwadged to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that Citie,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. Ho. 5. 2d Pop. Ant.</note> he ſaid; <hi>We haue made a happie change: yet this I dare ſay, if you reforme not your corruptions and ſinnes, though this cloude be ouer, we ſhall ſee and ſuffer worſe things: for I haue euer beene more afraide of your ſecurity then of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours wrath.</hi> So ſay I, wee haue a happy change in reſpect how it was with vs this time three yeres, a happie change in reſpect of that which our cruell and bloody papiſts did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18377:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>vs vnto this time twelue-moneth: But this I dare ſay; If we doe not reforme our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions and manners, though this cloud bee ouer, yet we ſhall ſee and ſuffer more fearefull things, for whatſoeuer other mens opinions are, for my part I haue euer feared more the the ſecuritie of the land, then the wrath of God; becauſe the wrath of God (if we were not ſecure) were to be expiated, and appeaſed by our repentaunce, and turning vnto him: but we being ſecure and ſetled vpon the dregs of our ſinnes, there is no hope that the wrath of God ſhould bee remooued, but that he ſhould doe to vs, as is ſpoken heere: <hi>Cut off head, and taile, &amp;c.</hi> and that theſe ſhould bee but the beginning of ſorrows. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Pſal 42.1.9.</note> here is inſtruction for all chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an magiſtrates, who are called Gods, and are ſo by their office, and the communication of power and authoritie; that they deale thus with wicked and obſtinate malefactors, when their lenitie or their ſmaller corrections will not make them relinquiſh the former corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and returne to better manners, they ought to take them in hand, and to vſe more ſeueritie, and ſharpnes towards them; amongſt many I would preſſe this, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning one kind of offendors, who are the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt enemies of the kingdome of Chriſt; the groſſeſt idolaters of all the kingdomes of the world, and the moſt peſtilent enemies of this
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18377:16"/>kingdome and ſtate; I meane our ſeducing and ſeduced papiſts. In whom I rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, becauſe this day reuiues the memorie of their cruell deſignement, ſeeing they pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed that it ſhould haue beene the laſt day, when any ſhould haue ſpoken againſt them out of this place: pretending, they meant to to be the Lords executioners of this iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment here ſet downe by the Prophet; when they intended indeede to haue bin the diuels inſtruments to haue cut off from <hi>Jrael.</hi> from <hi>England,</hi> head and taile, braunch, and ruſh, in one day. Concerning theſe I ſay, when nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lenitie of the ſtate, nor ſmaller meanes, and mildenes, will ſerue to reduce them from their hereſies, and Idolatries, to make them conformable to the lawes of God, and the land; there ought now more ſeuerity to be vſed.<note place="margin">Pſal 119, 126.</note> And as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid to God; <hi>It is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for thee Lord to lay too thy hand for they have deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thy law:</hi> So it is time for you gods to lay to your hands, elſe they will deſtroy both the law and the land. That ſuch may, and ought to be ſeuerely dealt with, eſpecially ſuch as are ſeducers, and obſtinate, I thinke no man will put mee to prooue, neither doe I intend it; being that which I once manifeſted out of this place: ſince which, the whole ſtate in the honourable court of Parliament, haue mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted, their perſwaſion of the truth of this point; elſe why haue they enacted, eſtabliſhed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18377:16"/>and confirmed more ſeuere, yet moſt iuſt lawes, againſt them: for the execution of theſe lawes it is that I nowe ſpeake, and do vrge vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this grounde, that if you loue them, if you loue the Church and truth, if you loue your ſelues and the State, do not the worke of God &amp; of the king negligently. I ſay, if you loue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you muſt execute: for if that be true of <hi>Hierom. Ille haereticum interficit, &amp;c. he killes an hereticke who ſuffers him to be an hereticke:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cont. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lag. lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>but a iuſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them, is the quickning and putting life into them, that dying to their hereſie, they may liue to the Catholique faith;</hi> what more loue can bee ſhewed, then to execute the lawes with ſeueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie againſt them? And that of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De verbis Dom. ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cund. Iows. ſer. <hi>59.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Qui phreneticum ligat, &amp; qui lethargium excitat, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bobus moleſtus eſt, ambos amat.</hi> He that blindeth a man poſſeſſed with a frenſie, and wakeneth another oppreſſed with a lethargie, is indeed troubleſome to both, but louing and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to both. Now when as many of them are poſſeſſed with a ſpirit of frenſie, ſeeking to ſubuert and ouerturne all, though they and their friends periſh with it; ſome with a lethar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, or a ſpirit of ſlumber, hauing drunke of that golden Babiloniſh cup, and being laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleepe like <hi>Siſera</hi> with the milke of that har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot; you can not ſhew more loue then in bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſuch mad-men, and bringing them to their wits, and in wakening ſuch ſleepers by the due execution of your moſt iuſt lawes;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18377:17"/>for this will be the meanes to win the ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; becauſe, as fire ſoftneth mettall and makes it fit for the hammer, and for to bee eaſily wrought to any forme, ſo the rod and correction worketh the ſame effect in mens minds; and as <hi>Elihu</hi> in <hi>Iob,</hi> of Gods correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: So I,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 33.16.</note> of your corrections. <hi>They will open their eares;</hi> and make them both more tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and teachable, by which many may bee gained that elſe muſt periſh. But if you loue not them, yet if you tender the good of the Church, you muſt execute that you haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed: for how can it bee well with the vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, if the Foxes liue or be at libertie, which deſtroy the vines? how can it be well with the flocke and the Lambes of it, if the wolues be not taken and cut off? How with the field of Gods corne, while that <hi>Sampſon</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> (if I honour him not too much, or diſgrace the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther extreamlie, in making the compariſon) may haue ſuch foxes to tye taile to taile, and put fir bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds in them to ſend into our church? how can <hi>Iſrael</hi> enioy the land of <hi>Canaan</hi> in quiet, if thoſe curſed <hi>Cananits</hi> be not ſubdued as ſeruants to the congregation, or ſubuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as enemies? What greater loue can you ſhew more to the Church, Chriſtes vineyarde, his flock, Gods field, and the whole land, then in taking theſe foxes, in abandoning theſe moules, in abaſing or deſtroying theſe <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites,</hi> proceeding according to your iuſt laws,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18377:17"/>to conſiſcation of goods, to impriſonment, baniſhment, or death it ſelfe, according to the qualitie of their offences. But if you neither loue them, nor tender the good of the Church (as be it farre from me to thinke you ſhould not) yet if you loue your ſelues and the peace of the ſtate, you muſt execute with ſome roundneſſe, and ſeueritie. For conſider I pray you, and call to mind, how that when they enioyed all lenitie, the lawes being laid a ſleepe for the ſpace of ſixe yeares, or therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts, in the latter dayes of our late Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne of happie memorie, and for almoſt 3. yeares ſpace in the dayes of his ſacred Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and being in hope that they would not be wakened againſt them in haſte; yet for all that, they hammered, and hatched that cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and more tiſen barbarous deſignement againſt the ſtate: and ſo that they might be at once auenged of them, for their light yoakes and rods, they prouided for them in former times, though it were to the periſhing of many of their friends, they cared not; What thinke you now that you haue made their yoakes heauier, and prepared ſcourges, and ſcorpions for them, when they are defeated of that, whereupon they had ſet their reſt, when they are thus exaſperated, and made raging, as beares robbed of their whelpes, what thinke you? Nay can you thinke, that they are now idle, and not plotting, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18377:18"/>ſome new reuenge; and if it may bee ſome more ſtrange and helliſh miſchiefe: which if you preuent not by due execution of the law, to diminiſh, and weaken them, they will execute their cruelty, to the ruine &amp; confuſion of you and the whole ſtate, if they bee but ſuffered a while to gather ſtrength, and get power, anſwerable to their cruell minds. For who ſees not this, is more then blind; that poperie and crueltie, goe hand, in hand, if they haue power in their handes. Therefore if there be any loue to thoſe ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſoules, that they may be reformed; If any loue to the Church of God, that <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> may proſper: If any loue to your ſelues, and ſtate, that it may continue in peace, and you inioy your liues, and liuings, your wiues, and children, your comforts and contentment: as you are Gods, ſo ſhew it in being like to God: to deale iuſtly in ſeueritie, with theſe; when you ſee lenitie will not recouer, nor ſmaller puniſhments worke any correction with them, to mooue them, or remoue them, from their hereſies, and other corruptions. It is reported of <hi>Groſthead</hi> the renowmed B. of <hi>Lyncolne,</hi> that a little before his death, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of wicked courſes, holden by the <hi>Romamſts,</hi> whoſe ſcourge he was; he ſaid the Church ſhould neuer finde any eaſe, from the oppreſſiue burdens laid vpon her, nor bee deliuered from the <hi>Aegiptiacall</hi> bondage ſhe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18377:18"/>was holden in, til hir deliuerance was wrought, <hi>In ore Glady cruentand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> In the mouth of the ſword, all bathed in blood. Which I alleadge, not to perſwade crueltie and barbariſme, and helliſh maſſacring; which thoſe cruell <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> vſe in all places, when they can preuaile: but to perſwade Iuſtice, and the execution of iuſtice; being perſwaded in my ſelfe, (as I thinke thouſands more are beſides) that as he thought no deliuerance could bee wrought, but by the ſword: So no preſeruation of vs from thoſe burdens, and bondages, but <hi>In ore Glady Iuſtitiae,</hi> In the mouth of the ſword, executing Iuſtice vpon ſuch as would drawe vs that way. Weapons they ſay hoade peace. but if it be knowne that trauailers; either can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, or will not vſe them; it will bolden co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly theeues, and will make them dare to practiſe any thing; either againſt their liues or goods. Lawes are good things for the peace of a ſtate: &amp; are the very weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of their defence: but if offenders either find ſome not willing that haue power, or thoſe reſtrained, that haue will to execute; they will dare to do any thing. For the particular; If Courtiers for money will procure pardon for ſuch as haue offended (abuſing the lenitie of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie) or elſe ſome diſpenſation for the time to come; to ſuſpend the lawes againſt ſome greatones: If Iudges fauour them in their trialls, and Iuſtices in their commitments,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18377:19"/>one ſet at libertie, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: If Sheriffes, and other officers, bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe in their ſearching for them, and infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming againſt them: If when information is giuen, and the Iury hath found the indite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Clarkes and Officers both know how to doe it, and doe practiſe to ſmother of 20. or 30.5. or more of the principalleſt, and moſt daungerous: If I ſay they may ſinde this ſauour, and remiſſion of the lawes by theſe meanes: how bolde will they grow, and how will they inſult, that though the face of the lawe be againſt them, yet the edge is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from them? how vnlike ſhall this gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be to that which God vſeth in adding, and vſing more ſeueritie, when the ſmaller corrections preuaile not? how preiudiciall to the peace of the ſtate, and preſeruation of his Maieſtie, his poſteritie and people, both in reſpect of their inueterate malice, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperated ſtomacks? and in reſpect of Gods iuſtice, who cannot endure ſuch a ſinne, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſeuere iudgements: when neither the loue of the truth, is expreſſed; nor the hatred of hereſies, and his enemies purſued. When <hi>Ahab</hi> had let <hi>Benhadad</hi> the King of <hi>Aram</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape his hands, whom the Lord had deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into his hands: euen then whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had fully reſolued to deſtroy him, and the whole king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, there came vnto him a Prophet of the Lord and vnder a parable made him accuſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18377:19"/>himſelfe, &amp; then vttered the Lords meſſage. Thus ſaith the Lord:<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 20.42.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe thou haſt let goe out of thy hands, a man whom I appointed to die, thy life ſhall go for his life, &amp; thy people for his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> The Lord hath deliuered into your hands, men, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath appointed to puniſhment, ſome after this ſort, ſome after that, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the iuſtice of the law; and ſome to die, which are their principall ſeducers: If you let them goe, out of your hands, what can you expect but that Iudgement, your liues for theirs; and your people, for their people; your goods, libertie, and peace, for theirs? But to preuent this: as you are Gods, ſo ſhewe it in time, in vſing more ſeueritie, and yet but iuſt, againſt al who are irreconciliable, and irreuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table; ſpecially againſt their ſeducers, the ſeedes-men not of hereſies only, but of horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble treaſon, and confuſion of ſtate. The french ſtorie reporteth, that <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anorola,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. lib. <hi>8.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by many, for a Prophet (but ſure hee was a renounned man, for pietie and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) tolde the french King <hi>Charles</hi> the 8. he ſhould haue great proſperitie in his voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age into <hi>Italic,</hi> and that God would giue the ſword into his hand; and all this, to the end hee ſhould reforme the corrupt ſtate of the church: which if he did not performe, he ſhuld returne home againe with diſhonour; and God would reſerue the honour of this worke, for ſome other: and ſo it fell out. I am no
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18377:20"/>Prophet, nor the ſonne of a Prophet; yet out of Gods dealing in former times, as the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, and Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtories ſhew, I may be bolde to ſpeake thus much; that ſeeing God hath put the ſword into your hands, to reforme things amiſſe, and withſtand corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that would grow by cutting off ſuch as ſeeke to bring them in: If you doe it, well and good;<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30.</note> 
               <hi>I will honour them that honour me:</hi> But if you doe it not, you ſhall returne with diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to your long homes. <hi>For they who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe me, ſhall be deſpiſed:</hi> and God will reſerue the honour of this worke to ſome other. Ther is a ſpeech in <hi>Lactantius</hi> to this purpoſe: If ſaith he,<note place="margin">De Ira Dei.</note> a maiſter of a family, ſhall haue his children maſſacred, his wife murdered, his houſe burned ouer his head, and all by a leawd ſeruant: and if he ſhould ſpare that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant and let him goe without ſeuere puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; what doe you thinke of him? Were he to be accounted mild, mercifull, and cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; or vnnaturall, and cruell? doubtleſſe euery one would condemne him of crueltie. Then what may be thought of your ſparing of Papiſts; for though (Bleſſed be God) they haue not done any ſuch thing to vs; yet there wanted no will nor intent in them: no inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour was lacking to haue effected it: So, no thanke to them, we yet liue and proſper; for if they might haue had their wills, long ſince our wiues and children had bin murdered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18377:20"/>our eyes, our houſes burned before our faces, our whole ſtate brought to confuſion. Then iudge whether pittie, &amp; lenitie to them, be not crueltie, to all our ſtate. But as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> hauing reprooued the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> ſomewhat ſharpely, ſaith;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>Beloued, wee haue perſwaded our ſelues, better things of you, and ſuch as accompanie ſaluation, though wee thus ſpeake:</hi> So, Honorable, and Reuerend, I haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded my ſelfe better things of you, and ſuch as accompanie the ſafetie of the ſtate, the peace of the Church, the proſperitie, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of his Maieſtie, and all his royall iſſue; and the good &amp; comfort of your ſelues and your poſteritie, though I thus ſpeake.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> this may perſwade euery man to indeuor for repentance, to profit by gods for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and leſſer iudgements, that they may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde the future and greater. Thoſe Patients who will not obey the phyſitians preſcripts, muſt indure his potions; and if thoſe whoſe ingredients are more gentle and milde and of leſſe malignitie, preuaile not, they muſt haue ſharper, if the phyſitian purpoſe to cure them: he that would auoyde theſe, muſt inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour himſelfe to helpe the firſt, that they may haue their effect, and worke that which was intended by them: ſo he that will not obey God commanding, muſt be ſure to heare from him; and to feele his rodde, that neglects his worde: and if he profit not by the leſſe, he ſhal
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18377:21"/>haue the greater: and ſeeing God will do this, he ought by that he hath felt, to harken to the prophet <hi>Ames, Prepare to meete him with true repentance, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to him that hath ſmitten him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos.</hi> 4.12.</note> leaſt his hand be ſtretched out ſtill. The phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians haue a potion againſt the plague, which conſiſteth of three ingredie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: but it is but the rich mans phyſicke, it is too coſtly for many, the medicine is called <hi>flying,</hi> the ingredients are theſe; <hi>Citò, longè, Tardè. Citò,</hi> flee ſoone enough: <hi>Longè,</hi> flee farre inough: <hi>Tardè,</hi> make no haſte to returne, but returne ſlowe inough. Many take this preſeruatiue, &amp; many are kept all together from this, though ouertaken with another: many haue it adiourned for a time, but yet are met withall afterwards, either with that or a greater:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos.</hi> 5.19.</note> As <hi>Amos</hi> ſaith; <hi>As if a man did ſlie from a lyon, and a Beare me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> him, or went into the houſe and leaned his hard againſt the wall and the Serpent bit him.</hi> But the prophets haue ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preſeruatiue not againſt this only, but all other, either to make them not touch him, or elſe to turne to his good; and this they call not flying, but returning. The ingredients of this medicine are two, laid downe euery where in the Scriptures: <hi>Ceaſe to do euill; learne to do well. Eſchew euill, and do good.</hi> And this is both reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue, &amp; preſeruatiue, that by which men may remooue the preſent, and preuent greater to come: for if men would turne from their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked waves and put away their drunkennes and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18377:21"/>gluttonie, their chambering &amp; wantonneſſe, their horible oathes and blaſphemie, ceaſe profaning of holy things and the Sabbothes of God, forſake their couetouſnes and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, vſurie, iniuſtice, adulterie, theft, and ſuch like and giue themſelues to practiſe ſobrietie, to refraine their tongues, to honour the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bothes and holy things, to followe chaſtitie, to be iuſt and faithfull, to ſeek iudgement, relieue the oppreſſed, iudge the fatherleſſe, and defend the widow; then as <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith of ſinnes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay.</hi> 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>though your ſinne were as crimſin, they ſhalbe made white as ſnow, &amp;c.</hi> So for the puniſhments of them, if they were neuer ſo great he wil remoue them, and the euill that is feared ſhall not come, as <hi>Chriſoſt.</hi> vrged the people of <hi>Antioch.</hi> with the example of the barbarous <hi>Niniuitos.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hom.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo non admirabile. What an admirable thing is it,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>That when the Iudge had pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſentence, the guiltie perſons ſhould by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance diſſolue it: they did not flee out of the Citie as we now doe, but abiding at home did diſannull the ſentence: they heard their houſes ſhould fall vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their heads, but they did flee from their ſinnes, none of them did forſake his owne houſe as wee doe now, but euery one departed from his wicked way: They ſaid not, the walles haue brought, and begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten this anger; wee who are authors of this wound, let vs prepare the medicine: therefore they tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted not for ſafetie to the change of place, but to the change, and mutation of their maners. Theſe things
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18377:22"/>the</hi> Barbarians <hi>did; and are not wee aſhamed to doe the contrary? If any of vs were angry with his ſeruant, and he ſhould not ſeeke to appeaſe our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but get him into his chamber, and begin to gather his clothes and ſtuffe together, and make a packe of them, and prepare to flee away; would wee eaſily beare this contempt?</hi> And ſhall wee thinke God will take it at our hands? Let vs then imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the <hi>Niniuites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ionah.</hi> 3.9.</note> who vpon vneertainties repented: for all they had, was but this, <hi>Who can tell whether God will turne, and repent; and turne away from his ſierce wrath, that wee periſh not?</hi> For they knew not the law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: but wee haue a certaintie; namely, a moſt ſure word: euen the certaine promiſes of God. Let vs, as we haue more incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments then they, turne to God. But to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this poynt, I would ſay as the Prophet <hi>Gad</hi> ſaid to <hi>Dauid,</hi> when hee had deliuered Gods fearefull meſſage vnto him, touching the choyee of his plague: <hi>Wilt thou that ſeuen yeares famine come vpon thee in thy land? Or wilt thou flee three monethes before thine enemies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.13.</note> 
               <hi>they following thee? Or that there bee three daies peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence in thy land? Now aduiſe thee, and ſee what anſwere I ſhall giue to him that ſent me.</hi> So ſay I, aduiſe your ſelues, and ſee what aunſwere I ſhall giue to him that ſent mee. Let mee not ſay, that you will not returne, for that is not profitable for you, nor ioyfull newes for me to carie: But if I ſhall ſay to God, you will
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18377:22"/>returne, then as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezod.</hi> 8.29.</note> 
               <hi>Let not</hi> Pharaoh <hi>deceiue any more:</hi> So let not <hi>Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> deceiue any more: For, <hi>Be not deceiued, God is not mocked:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.7.</note> 
               <hi>for, whatſoeuer a man ſowes that ſhall he reape.</hi> He that ſowes repentance, ſhall reape mercie; and he that ſowes obſtinacie and hardnes of heart ſhall reape confuſion: for God ſhall multiply his plagues ſtill vpon him, and his wrath ſhall not be turned away; but his hand ſhall bee ſtretched out ſtill.</p>
            <p>So much may ſuffice for the generall cauſe of this threatened iudgement.</p>
            <p>In the next place, as they are here placed by the Prophet, followeth the iudgement it ſelfe. Whereof I haue many things to ſpeake: but the time paſſing ſo faſt, and being much ſpent alreadie; I ſhall bee forced to imitate cunning painters, who hauing in a great ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry many pictures to expreſſe in a little table, onely draw the chiefeſt and moſt principall at large, and in their full proportions, the reſt they expreſſe by the heads, and the halues onely: So I ſhall bee conſtrained to touch many things briefly, that I may han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle the chiefeſt more fully; then by the halues, that I may follow theſe ſomewhat at the full. The next thing then which is to bee handled, is the generalitie of the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, in theſe words; <hi>The Lord will cut off head and taile, braunch, and ruſh.</hi> Whence, for our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, I obſerue this point.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18377:23"/>This is the dealing of God when he commeth to viſite; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> Where he findeth ſinne generally ſpreade ouer all, then will he bring a generall iudgement vpon all: this is manifeſt through the ſcriptures, when ſinne grewe generall in the world,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5.7.</note> 
               <hi>and the Imaginations of mans hart was only euill continually: then</hi> the Lord brought a general deluge of water and deſtroyed all, ſaue <hi>Noe</hi> &amp; his family:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 1 8.</note> when ſinne couered <hi>Sodome, Gomorrah,</hi> and the fiue Citties about it, ſo that not ten good men could be found in all thoſe Cities: there came a common fire from heauen and deſtroyed all; when ſinne in the daies of <hi>Dauid</hi> couered the people, and <hi>Dauid</hi> left to his owne corruption, numbered the people,<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 21.12.13.</note> and prouoked the Lord, there came a common plague vpon them from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Berſheba:</hi> Alſo when <hi>Manaſſes</hi> and the people corrupted themſelues with Idolatrie, the Lord threate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s he would bring a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> plague vpon them, <hi>that he would ſtretch ouer them the line of</hi> Samaria, <hi>and the plummet of the houſe of</hi> Ahab, <hi>and would wipe Ieruſalem as a man would wipe a diſh, and turneth it vpſide downe:</hi> by al theſe it is manifeſt, that where ſinne is general, there Gods iudgements ſhall be generall.</p>
            <p>The reaſon of this is, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> Firſt, becauſe Iuſtice requireth alwaies a proportion betwixt the ſin and the puniſhment: &amp; that both in the weight and greatnes of it, and in the length and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of it: when the ſinnes are great and crying
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:18377:23"/>ſinnes, the puniſhments muſt be great and heauie plagues; ſo when they are generally ſpread ouer all, proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> requireth the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments alſo ſhould be generall. Secondly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by this, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> God may manifeſt and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his power: for, as it ſhewes his power <hi>to ſaue with fewe as well as with many.</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.6. ſo to deſtroy many as well as fewe: &amp; though <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpared <hi>Ioab becauſe he was weake and but newly anoynted King, and the ſonnes of</hi> Seruia <hi>were too ſtrong for him;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.39.</note> yet God is King from euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, yea none is too ſtrong for him: but as well when hand ioyneth in hand, the wicked ſhall not be vnpuniſhed, as when they are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle.</p>
            <p>Now vpon this ground, and from hence may I teach our earthly gods, that ſeeing the heauenly God will deale thus: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> So ought our earthly gods to imitate, not to ſuffer vnpuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, nor to tollerate any iniquitie, or any workers of iniquity; becauſe of the multitude, or that many are wrapped in the ſame ſinne: eſpecially when they are not ſo many, but their power is able to deale with them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out preiudice to the whole,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Parmeu. Cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> and common peace. Indeed <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath a rule, that it is not ſafe puniſhing of him, who being corrupt hath a multitude of companions: but when many are corrupted, nothing remaines to the godly, but <hi>Dolor &amp; Gemitus, Mourning and gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning:</hi> That by this figue they may be found
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18377:24"/>fit and worthy to eſcape their deſtruction: as <hi>Ezeke.</hi> 9. But this by himſelfe is expounded, that it is either of the cenſure of the Church or elſe of the Magiſtrate, when he cannot do it without preiudice to the common good; for ſo he manifeſteth it, out of <hi>Mathew:</hi> Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Tares, the Seruants ſaid vnto him, <hi>Wilt thou that we goe and gather them vp? But he ſaid nay:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 13.28.29.</note> 
               <hi>leaſt whilſt you goe about to gather the Tares yee plucke vp alſo with them the wheate:</hi> ſo that when the Tares come to be plucked vp, and the feare of hurting the wheate is remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and that it is in no daunger, and the iniquitie either hath not defenders, or no ſuch defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders that ſuch a daungerous ſchiſme and rent may follow; then ſaith he, <hi>Ne Dorm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at ſeueritas diſcipliuae, Let not the ſeucritie of the law ſleepe.</hi> Now among vs there are no ſuch malefactors, but the power of the ſtate may well deale with, though in many ſinnes many are combined: therefore ought they not to ſuffer them vnpuniſhed for their multitude. Truth it is, our pope-holy Catholiques, who are combined in Idolatrie and treaſon, are many, and they let not to brag of their mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tvde, as if they would dare the ſtate to deale with them: nay plainely daring the ſtate, as D. Biſhop doth in his Epiſtle to his Maieſty, before his anſwere to M. <hi>Perkins;</hi> Telling the ſtate, what a multitude they are, &amp; what neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie may compell them vnto: yet bleſſed be
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:18377:24"/>God, the ſonnes of <hi>Seruia,</hi> or of the three headed <hi>Cerberus,</hi> are not too ſtrong for vs; howſoeuer they may growe by the conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uence, and lenitie of the ſtate, and the prone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our people to that naturall religion, or idolatrous ſuperſtition. Therefore ought you earthly gods to imitate the heauenly; and let your puniſhments bee generall, becauſe they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe this iniquitie to be very general: eſpecially ſeing this time twelue-month they thought to goe generally to worke, both with you, and vs all; yea, ſeeing wee haue a voice from heauen ſpeaking this to vs, and commaunding that you ſhould doe ſo, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward her euen as ſhe hath rewarded you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 18.6.</note> 
               <hi>and giue hir double, according to hir workes: and in the cuppe, that ſhee hath filled to you, fill her the dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> If any will ſay, All are not ſuch; and it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt charitie, ſo to iudge of all: I aunſwere him, I haue learned to put a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt popiſhly affected, and grounded papiſts: howbeit, it is apparant that they that are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly popiſh, are ſo blockiſh, that without the ſeueritie of the lawes, they will hardly har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to any inſtruction. And as for grounded Papiſts, which are indeed Atheiſts, and trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; howſoeuer it may be thought all are not alike cruellie minded; as ſome haue ſhewed themſelues more then barbarous: yet if they might haue but a little ſchooling, of a Ieſuite, or a ſecular Prieſt (for if there be one good,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18377:25"/>there is neuer a bad) they will eaſily be harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: and they that now ſeeme to be moſt pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, if they had had that they looked for, (but let their eyes fall out, before they ſee it) they would haue beene like the <hi>Edomites</hi> that <hi>Obadiah</hi> ſpeaketh of,<note place="margin">Obadiah. Verſe. <hi>12.13.14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>They would haue beheld vs in the day that we ſhould haue bin made ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers; they would haue reioyced ouer vs in the day of our deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; they would haue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proudly in the day of our afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; they would haue entred into our gates in the day of our deſtruction; they would haue looked on our affliction in the day of our deſtruction; in the day of our deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they would haue laid hands on our ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te; in the day of our deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they would haue ſtood in the croſſe wayes, to cut them off that had eſcaped, and haue ſhut vp the remembrance of vs, in thè day of our affliction.</hi> Therefore bleſſed ſhal that hand be,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137.13.</note> that in the way of iuſtice, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardeth them as they would haue ſerued vs.</p>
            <p>Secondly, from hence, and by this, may I admoniſh al men, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> not to bleſſe themſelues in their ſinnes; nor to thinke they may bee the more ſecure, becauſe wickedneſſe is ſpread o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer al, euen <hi>head &amp; taile, branch and ruſh.</hi> Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſuch is the corruption of men, that the corruptions of the time they take to be a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient couer for whatſoeuer ſinnes they lie in; and while they compare themſelues with others, they neither are afraid, nor aſhamed of ſinne. For where the number is ſo great, there is euery thing more tollerable: as, in the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18377:25"/>region where all are borne black-mores, it is no ſhame for any to bee blacke; and in thoſe regions where al are drunkards, it's no ſhame to be drunke: So where wicked men are ſo many, and ſinne ſo familiar, it is neither fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red nor auoided. But alas, ſee the folly and madneſſe of theſe men; that they make moſt for their ſecuritie, will ſooneſt bring their ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine; becauſe that when ſinne is generall, then commeth the generall iudgement: while there are but fewe particular offenders, God vſeth long patience to men; but when they are once growne to be banded in ſinne, and all to conſent in wickednes, then God cannot but aſſemble al his armies againſt them; as a prince whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath one rebell vp againſt him with a ſmal power, litle regards him: but when they are growne to a multitude, he muſtereth and ſendeth his forces againſt them. We ſee how God hath dealt with vs, and he threate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to deale with vs further: for are we better then <hi>Dauid</hi> and his people and others? And if this ſeeme not to bee generall enough, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the noble, the worſhipfull and the rich, are but a little troubled, and touched with it, ſeeing they can take the Phyſitians preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, ſo that this hath onely beene the plague of the poore, and of the ſeruants, not of the maiſters, and the rich: Let vs know that the Lord will yet puniſh vs, more generally. And if wee turne not as the <hi>Niniuites,</hi> with one
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18377:26"/>heart as one man, that our repentance and humiliation may be generall as our ſinne and corruptions haue beene, hee will puniſh vs yet more, as he is able, and moſt iuſt; and hee will ſtretch ouer vs the line of <hi>Samariae,</hi> and the Plummet of the houſe of <hi>Ahab,</hi> and hee will wipe vs cleane; as a diſh that is wiped, and turned vp-ſide downe. And thus you haue the generality of this iudgement. Now I come to the impartiallitie of it, that it is to the <hi>head</hi> as well as the <hi>taile;</hi> and to the <hi>branch,</hi> as well as to the <hi>ruſh:</hi> whence obſerue,</p>
            <p>That when God commeth to iudge, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label> hee ſpares none for any outward reſpects, though they be high in honour, great in power, rich in reuenues, wiſe in policie, deepe in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or whatſoeuer elſe: no outward thing is any priuiledge to ſaue them, from his Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rou.</hi> 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> Hence is that of <hi>Salomon; Though hand ioyne in hand, the wicked ſhall not bee vnpuniſhed:</hi> So, though head ioyne to head, and all the meanes bee winded and knit together that may be had, yet ſhall nothing free them from the iudgements of God. Such are the vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie of the Lords arrowes, when he ſhoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them abroad;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 2.31.</note> though <hi>Achab</hi> bee in the middeſt of his hoaſt, companied with all his men of armes, yet one of them ſhall giue him a deadly wound. Though <hi>Nabuchadnezzer</hi> be in his lordly palace, built for the honour of his maieſtie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> accompanied with his wiſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18377:26"/>counſell, yet another of them ſhall ſmite him, and driue him to baniſhment. Though <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhazzer</hi> his ſonne be in the middeſt of his cuppes; euen as it were in deſpight of God, drinking healthes in the veſſells of Gods ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle: yet another of them ſhall be like an <hi>hand-writing vpon the wall, and ſhall make his countenance to change,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Daniel. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>his thoughts to be trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, his ioyntes to looſe, and his knees to beate one againſt the other.</hi> Though <hi>Herod</hi> be arrayed with his royall robes, ſet vpon his glorious ſeate, making his eloquent oration, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying the applauſe of the people,<note place="margin">Acts. <hi>12</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The voyce of God and not of man:</hi> Yet ſhall another of them ſmite him, that hee ſhall bee eaten with wormes, and make him as loathſome to the ſmel, as euer he was delectable to the eare. If the Lord ſmite the Cedars of <hi>Libanus,</hi> how ſhall the <hi>ſhrubs</hi> eſcape? for ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>The voyce of the Lordſh tketh the Codars of Liba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, aſwel as the ſhrubs of Cades,</hi> wherby we plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee, that there is no earthly thing can be a writ of protection, to protect a man from the wrath of God, when hee commeth to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And good reaſon there is, why it ſhould not.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe the Lord is no accepter of perſons, as <hi>Peter</hi> thought in his error; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niouſly confeſſing it afterwards, <hi>Acts.</hi> 10.34. And the reaſon of this, is partly the iuſtice and vprightnes of his nature, and partly the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:18377:27"/>greatneſſe of his maieſtie: the vprightneſſe of his nature, becauſe it is immutable, and he alwayes the ſame; the greatneſſe of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, becauſe nothing is great in compariſon of him, as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> giueth the reaſon; though the things be great in reſpect of man, yet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is great in reſpect of God, ſeeing that as <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpeakes;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay.</hi> 40.22.</note> 
               <hi>Hee ſitteth vpon the Circle of the earth, &amp; the inhabitants thereof are as graſhoppers.</hi> The earth is but as a poynt, or mote in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the heauens: though a little hill in reſpect of man, is a great thing. A litle grain turneth the goldſmiths ſcales; when as a great matter will not change the ſcales at the Kings beame.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> becauſe their ſinnes are greater then others: partly becauſe they haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed much, and much is required of them; and where moſt obedience is due, there the diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience is greater: partly becauſe, where o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſinne of infirmitie, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaketh of the theefe, that <hi>he ſteales for hunger, therefore men pittie him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 6.30.</note> But they ſinne of contempt, as <hi>Pharoh</hi> did: <hi>Who is the Lord, that I ſhould feare him?</hi> partly, becauſe by their example, many are drawne and imboldened to the like ſinnes: therefore no maruell if God ſmite them principallie.</p>
            <p>Now from this poynt, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> the impartialitie of Gods iudgements, may we haue theſe infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations: Firſt, for ſuch as <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> ſpeaketh,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18377:27"/>
               <hi>Who execute the iudgements, not of max,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.6.</note> 
               <hi>but of God;</hi> They ought to doe as God himſelfe would doe, whoſe deputies they are, and whoſe perſon they repreſent; who alſo is in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of them, not to ſpare any malefactor, for any outward reſpect, whatſoeuer: they ought to puniſh the Noble, as well as the baſe, the rich, as the poore, the great as wel as the ſmal. It was not for nought, that <hi>Iethro</hi> aduiſed <hi>Moſes</hi> that his magiſtrates ſhould bee <hi>men of courage, and hating Couetonſnes:</hi> becauſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.21.</note> they that are fearefull, and that loue money, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to finger it, will ſinne for a little thing; a ſmall thing will eaſily turne them, and one graine will make their ſcale weigh heauier, or lighter. They will ſoone bee like the fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Angle, as one ſaith, that though it haue but a little fiſh it will bend ſomewhat: but when it hath a great fiſh, it will bowe to his hand; but theſe things ſhould not be ſo. But as the lawe, which is the dumbe magiſtrate, was penned without reſpect of perſon: So the magiſtrate which is the ſpeaking lawe, ſhould execute without any affection; as well puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Noble adulterer, as a meane one; as well laying the law to a great idolatrous recuſant, as to a ſmall one; as well to ſuch as is his friend, as to him that is a ſtranger; as well to him that hath many friends, as to him that is deſtitute of friends; and not onely to thoſe that openly profeſſe that groſſe idolatrie, but
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:18377:28"/>to ſuch as vnderhand further that peſtilent ſuperſtition. How daungerous ſuch are, may appeare by that which <hi>Socrates</hi> writeth: that certaine <hi>Arians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Socrates. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Cap. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> ſuppoſed to be conuerts, abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the lenitie and credulitie of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> the great, inſinuated themſelues into his fauour; and obtained offices, and imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in the common-wealth: theſe pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely profeſſed the doctrine of the <hi>Nieene</hi> Creed; but ſecretly, and vnderhand they kept their olde corruptions in their hearts: and by all meanes they could, collaterallie with ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and Iniuſtice, through the ſides of the godly, they wounded the holy and innocent cauſe. If there be any ſuch among vs, poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing any ſuch places; and if there bee any branch of the law againſt them, theſe as moſt dangerous ought to feele the waight of it: but if there be no lawe, bleſſed be his mouth that will ſpeake for ſuch a law, that there may bee more and longer triall made of them, before they be admitted to any place; and if they be in any, that they may bee ſpeedily remooued when their windings are diſcouered: &amp; bleſſed he his hand that ſhall execute ſuch a law. And as againſt them, ſo againſt all other malefac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, executions ought to be without parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alitie: and then if they prooue like vnto <hi>Leui</hi> in execution,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.9.</note> 
               <hi>That ſaid vnto his father, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I haue not ſeene him; neither knew hee his brethren nor his owne children: for they obſerued
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:18377:28"/>thy law, and and kept thy couenant:</hi> If any deale ſo, then ſhall come vpon them that bleſſing, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>11</label> 
               <hi>The Lord ſhall bleſſe their ſubſtance, and accept the worke of their hands, and ſmite through the loynes of them that riſe againſt him, and of them that hate him, that they riſe not againe.</hi> But if any be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall, let him looke for the recompence of King <hi>Saul,</hi> who was put out of the calendar of the Kings, as if hee had raigned but two yeares: ſo ſhal they, out of the number of the worthy Iudges of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this may admoniſh all thoſe that are great, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> whoſe heads the Lord hath lifted vp aboue others, who are more Noble, honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, worſhipfull or wealthy, then others that thinke themſelues in greateſt ſecuritic, the Lord can bring them to greateſt miſeries. For it is he that can binde the Nobles in chaines, and Princes in links of Iron: his darknes coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Courte of <hi>Pharoh,</hi> as well as the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie of <hi>Aegytt:</hi> he ſlewe the firſt borne of the King, as well as the pezants of <hi>Ham: Pharoh</hi> was deſtroyed in the red Sea, as well as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Souldier or ſubiect. That which <hi>Dauid</hi> ſent as a comfort to <hi>Ioab</hi> after worthie <hi>Vriah</hi> was ſlaine <hi>(Let not this thing trouble thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.25.</note> 
               <hi>the ſword of the Lord deſtroyes one as well as another)</hi> I may ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d as a cooling card to thoſe that are at eaſe in <hi>Sion,</hi> &amp; ſecure in <hi>England;</hi> lifted vp, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wings of their wealth, or other priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges: but yet with this charge; <hi>Let this thing
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:18377:29"/>trouble you; for the ſword of the Lord deuoureth one as well as an other.</hi> The iudgements of God are vpon vs: they haue little profited thoſe, that haue any of theſe priuiledges; partly for that they are ſeduced with a conceit, which is, that wee neither read of, nor ſee any men of their qualitie touched with any ſuch plague: but do they thinke ſo indeed? Why then did they flie from it? What a vaine action is it to flie, when there is no feare? But, haue not as great as they bin ſmitte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with it? What, was not <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah</hi> ſmitten to death with it? And was <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids</hi> feare a vaine feare, when the Angell ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached towards <hi>Ieruſalem?</hi> But if this ſhould not be, hath not the Lord varietie of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? and hath he not ſmitten others as great as they, with as fearefull as this? If <hi>Pharaoh</hi> could not be preſerued with all his iron Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots, if the goodly buildings and houſes of <hi>Nabuchadnezzar</hi> could not preſerue him from his beaſtly baniſhment, nor the praiſe and the great applauſe of the people keepe <hi>Herod</hi> from the deuouring of the wormes, nor all the full barnes of the rich man in the Goſpell, could keepe his ſoule in body for one night; What can your great power, or goodly buildings, or honours, or admiration of men promiſe ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie vnto you? and yet if they do promiſe, how can they performe it? And if they could in this life, yet ſhould they not in the life that is to come: where if God would reſpect perſons,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:18377:29"/>yet there ſhould not be any thing to be reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, becauſe euery one ſhall appeare ſtript of all worldly priuiledges; Princes of their Crownes and dignities, Nobles of their Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets and honours, the rich of their wealth, the magiſtrate of their Scarlets &amp; of their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes of honour, and euery one ſhall appeare more naked then he goeth out of the world. In this world indeed there is a difference, but none in the world to come: but as it is with marchants counters, that all the time the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count laſteth, one is better then another, one ſtands for a thouſand, another for a hundred, and another for a cypher; but when the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count is ended, all is alike: So it is in theſe things. Let no man then for his greatneſſe, honour, worſhip, wealth, or any other thing, flatter himſelfe in his ſinnes, as if the hand of God ſhould not finde him out here in this preſent world: ſeeing he will <hi>cut off head,</hi> as well as <hi>taile, branch</hi> as <hi>ruſh;</hi> much leſſe let him harden himſelfe, in reſpect of the time to come. For whereas riches and theſe thinges when they are had, will not deliuer their ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in the day of wrath; he cannot expect, but falſelie, deliuerance, by them, when he ſhall appeare without them.</p>
            <p>Now further out of this, that God will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy both <hi>head,</hi> and <hi>taile,</hi> the deceiued magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, &amp; the deceiuing Prophet, as it is inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted in the 15. verſe, which is the vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:18377:30"/>and the equitie of Gods iudgement; I obſerue this doctrine: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>4</label>
            </p>
            <p>That wicked magiſtrats and miniſters, flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering and bolſtering each others in their wicked courſes, ſhall certainly be puniſhed, and oftentimes together. So it is manifeſt by <hi>Balaam</hi> and the Kings of <hi>Midian:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nomb</hi> 3 1. <hi>Kings.</hi> 18.22. 1. <hi>Kings.</hi> 13.33.23. <hi>Ier.</hi> 3.49.</note> alſo by <hi>Ahab</hi> &amp; his ſoure hundred falſe Prophets: by <hi>Ierohoam</hi> and his hedge prieſts: by <hi>Zedchia</hi> and his falſe prophets, when as <hi>Ieremy,</hi> and other the poore people were reſerued. And why this?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> But firſt, becauſe they do much hurt by their example, &amp; ſtrengthen other mens hands in ſinne, being the cauſe of the corruptions of others; the whole bodie being commonly as theſe heads are. So that it is in a common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, as one ſaith it is in a fiſh, that if the head bee once corrupted and putrified, the whole body certainely is no leſſe; and if a man would know whether the bodie of the fiſh be corrupt or no, hee muſt ſmell the head: ſo if theſe heads be corrupted, the whole bodie needes muſt be infected. Theſe are the ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaders and captaines of ſuch rebellions: it is iuſt then they ſhould be puniſhed with the firſt and together.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> becauſe the Lord would ſhewe both his iuſtice and his power, in one action: his iuſtice giuing <hi>aequalia aequalibus,</hi> puniſhing alike them, who ſinne alike; and power, in
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:18377:30"/>manifeſting that no ſtrength is able to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand him, but that he is able to confound all that combine themſelues:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nahum.</hi> 1.9.10.</note> euen as <hi>Nahum</hi> ſaith, <hi>They ſhall be but as thornes folden together, as drunkards in their drunkennes: they ſhal be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured as ſtubble fully dried.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if theſe things ſhall bee thus; Firſt, magiſtrates may learne to know who are their friends, and who their enemies. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> In the generall it will bee granted, that he that preſerues a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from deſtruction, is his ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al friend; he that draweth him into ruine muſt needs be his enemie; and ſuch an one is a flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer: who, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 29.5.</note> 
               <hi>ſpreads a net for his ſteps.</hi> And ſuch are flattering miniſters, who ſmoth them vp in euery thing, magnify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing euery thing that they doe, and is in them; as if no mote were at al in their garments; as if they could not ſinne, or that which is ſinne in others were no ſinne in them: theſe are they who bring deſtruction vnto them. There is a kinde of Serpent, that by ſtinging of men, caſts them into a maruellous ſweete ſleepe; who if euer they once wake, they preſently die: ſuch verily are theſe flatterers; and the like will be to theſe who are flattered, if they could, or would foreſee and know it. If <hi>Ahab</hi> could haue ſeene it, <hi>Micha</hi> was not his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, but <hi>Zidkiah</hi> &amp; the whole companie of falſe flattering prophets. If <hi>Ieroboam</hi> could haue ſeene it, plaine dealing <hi>Amos</hi> was not
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:18377:31"/>his enemie, but flattering <hi>Amaziah,</hi> the prieſt: So generally to all princes, ſuch mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, are enemies, who compoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to their countenances, and ſeeke not to frame them to the lawes of God; who are like to ſome pictures that will looke on a man which way ſoeuer hee looke, on the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, or on the left; before him, or aſide of him. The Lord keepe all Chriſtian Kings, from ſuch enemies. And eaſie were it for them to be freed of them, if they would countenance thoſe that would deale plainely with them, with diſcretion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 25.23.</note> and diſcountenance all ſuch ſmoothers and flatterers. For the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>as the North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winde driueth away the raine: ſo would an angry cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance, the ſlandering tong;</hi> yea, <hi>the flattering tongue.</hi> I ſuppoſe that <hi>Alexander</hi> was a long time after free from flatterers, when as <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulus,</hi> hauing read vnto him many things that he had writ of him ſurpaſſing the truth, as the was paſſing the riuer <hi>Hydaſpis;</hi> he tooke the booke from him, and threwe it into the riuer, and ſaid, hee was almoſt mooued to doe ſo with <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> himſelfe, for his ſeruile dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: with ſuch kind of entertainment, they might eaſily rid the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, of ſuch deſtroying flatterers; leaſt they be forced to ſay as <hi>Adrian</hi> the Emperour, when he was a dying (hauing delighted in Phyſitians all his life, who ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred nothing but pleaſing things vnto him,) ſaid; that too many Phyſitians had kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:18377:31"/>the Emperor: ſo too many flatterers, haue cauſed their deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Secondly, miniſters may learnes, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> as they loue themſelues, to deale faithfully, and to bee as the Cherubines, vnto the mercie ſeate, thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they looked and thence they gaue their aunſweres; and <hi>not to be partiall in the law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.11</note> leaſt God cauſe them to bee deſpiſed, and in the end deſtroy them, as here is threatned. They may liue in a time, when ſuch prophets <hi>as will ſpeake of wine, and ſtrong drinke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mich.</hi> 2.11.</note> and pleaſing things, ſhall be moſt deſired; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſuch as are like thoſe in <hi>Eſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.10.</note> 
               <hi>which ſay vnto the ſeers, ſee not, and to the Prophets, prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie not vnto vs right things, but ſpeake flattering things vnto vs, prophecie errors:</hi> and ſuch as will tell them if they deale faithfully, as <hi>Balacke</hi> told <hi>Balaam, I thought ſurely to promote thee to honour, but the Lord hath kept thee backe from ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 24.11.</note> And ſo it proues that this is the way to earthly honour, preferment, and liuing for a ſeaſon and a little while: but the Lord threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it ſhall not proſper long with them, he can in a night take all from them as he did <hi>Ionaſ</hi> his gourd. But if they enioy it longer, it is but for a while;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 17.5.</note> for <hi>the eyes of his children ſhall faile, that ſpeaketh flattery to his friends.</hi> But if no ſuch thing happen to them in this life, what haue they gained to gaine the whole world, to get all honour and preferment, and loſe their owne ſoules, and to anſwere for ſo many ſoules
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:18377:32"/>as haue periſhed through their vnfaithfulnes? For what can they anſwere when God ſhall come to iudge? will they pretend the greatnes of thoſe, whom they indeuoured ſo to pleaſe? certainly it will not benefit them.<note place="margin">Hom. <hi>28.</hi> ad pop. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio.</note> 
               <hi>Chryſostome</hi> when he had ſpoken ſomewhat which ſeemed to offend the rich and mighty of his audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſpake to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thus; <hi>Ne quis miht diues. &amp;c. Let no rich man, nor no great or powerful man, ſwell againſt me, or knit his browes at me; I account of all theſe as fables, ſhaddowes, and dreames: for none of thoſe that are preſent ſhall be able to defend me at that day, when I ſhall be challenged and reprooued for not deliuering the lawe of God with ſufficient ſharpnes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>this was, euen this was the ruine of that admirable olde man, who himſelfe liued a blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les life: it deſtroyed him with his ſonnes;</hi> what then can any flattring <hi>Amaziahs</hi> or fawning <hi>Zedki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahs</hi> expect? that any mans greatnes ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them? it will not defend themſelues: how then their flatterers? nay as is ſaid before; they then ſhal haue none of their greatnes to defend themſelues or helpe others.</p>
            <p>Now in the 16. verſe followeth the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular cauſe of the iudgement, which is the gouernours and Miniſters miſleading of the people, making them to erre: whence it muſt needs be that they themſelues erred and teached errors. Whence I gather this.</p>
            <p>That the gouerners, rulers &amp; Miniſters of a particular viſible Church, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctri. </seg>5</label> may erre in matters
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:18377:32"/>of faith, and manners, doctrine and life, which is manifeſt through the whole booke of the Scriptures; Firſt theſe things were foretolde: for howſoeuer the people made a bragge, <hi>Come let vs imagine ſome deuice againſt Ieremiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 18.18.</note> 
               <hi>for the law ſhal not periſh fro the prieſt, nor counſell from the wiſe, nor the word from the Prophets:</hi> Yet the Lord he threateneth it ſhuld come to paſſe cleane contrary:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 7.26.</note> as it is ſaid in <hi>Ezek. Calamitie ſhal come vpon calamitie, &amp; rumour ſhal be vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor: then ſhal they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ke a viſion of the Prophet; but the law ſhal periſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Prieſt, &amp; counſel from the auncient:</hi> and Micha. 3.6. <hi>Therefore night ſhall be vnto you for a viſion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mich.</hi> 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>and darkneſſe ſhall be vnto you for a diuination; and the ſunne ſhall goe downe ouer the Prophets, and the day ſhall be darke ouer them.</hi> Secondly, it is manifeſt by that which is in <hi>Eſay, The watch men are all bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                     <desc>•••…</desc>
                  </gap>, they be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleepe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>and delight in ſleeping:</hi> and by that in <hi>Ieremie; I haue ſeene fooliſimeſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.13</note> 
               <hi>in the Prophets of</hi> Samariah, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If the exception be, that this was <hi>Iſrael</hi> and not <hi>Iuda,</hi> then ſee that which followeth; <hi>I haue alſo ſeene filthineſſe in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of Ieruſalem.</hi> If it be ſaid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 14.16.</note> that theſe are prophets and not prieſts; Thirdly, I manifeſt it by the euent. <hi>All the chieſe of the prieſts alſo and of the people, treſpaſſed wonderfully,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.14.</note> 
               <hi>according to all the abominations of the heathen, and polluted the houſe of the Lord, which hee had ſanctified in Ieruſalem.</hi> And if it be ſaid, that this was in the Synagogue &amp; not in the chriſtian church
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:18377:33"/>(as they abſurdly ſpeake) that all the cheiſe of the prieſts and of the people treſpaſſed, &amp;c. We will follow them whither they call vs: and ſee the Apoſtles how they erred: when Chriſt ſpake vnto them of his ſufferings, in <hi>Luke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.34.</note> it is ſaid; <hi>They vnderſtood none of theſe things, and this ſaying was hid from them: neither perceiued they the things which were ſpoken:</hi> which not vnderſtanding of the ſpeech of Chriſt, grew out of an error, which their mindes was foreſtalled withall before, that Chriſt ſhould raigne as a temporall king. But it may be that this was before Chriſts reſurectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; ſee therfore his diſciples asked him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 1.6.</note> ſaying; <hi>Lord wilt thou at this time reſtore the kingdoe to Iſrael?</hi> as drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of an earthly kingdome; as if he ſhould haue had one: but though he now were riſen, vet was he not aſcended; neither had ſent the holy ghoſt. The to ſay nothing touching cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the Church, &amp; thoſe in like lihood not a ſewe, who erred, concerning the calling of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> ſo that <hi>Peter</hi> was faine to make an Apologie for his going to <hi>Cornelius, Acts</hi> 11; Let vs come to <hi>Peter</hi> the head of the Church; <hi>Acts.</hi> 10.14. he was ignorant that by Chriſt the ceremoniall lawe was aboliſhed; <hi>I haue eaten nothing that is vncleane or polluted:</hi> yea himſelfe was ignorant of the calling of the Gentiles: <hi>doubt not but goe;</hi> therefore hee was ignorant before: and verſe 33.34. <hi>Of a truth, now I know there is no reſpect of perſons with God.</hi> And as he
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:18377:33"/>erred in faith, ſo alſo in manners. <hi>Gelat.</hi> 2.14, <hi>Paul reprooued him before all men, that being a Iewe, be walked as the Gentiles, and not like the Iewes: and yet compelled the Gentiles to dee like the Iewes:</hi> Is it not then manifeſt they may erre, and haue erred? but ſee this confirmed.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> Firſt, becauſe the beſt knoweth but in part; though their knowledge be neuer ſo great, yet is it but imperfect: for the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.9.</note> 
               <hi>Wee know in part, and wee prophecie in part:</hi> and the common ſpeech is, <hi>Maexima pars eorum quae ſci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>us, eſt minima pars eorum quae igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranuts; The greatest part of thoſe things we know, is the leaſt part of thoſe things we yet are ignorat of.</hi> Now ignorance is the mother of errour, ſaith <hi>Bernard:</hi> ſeeing al men the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are in partignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, they may erre: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Prieſt may erre in part.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> Secondly, becauſe euery man is but in part ſanctified, and hath the remnants of the olde man remaining in him: euen <hi>Paul,</hi> who had ſo farre proceeded in ſanctification, as that <hi>hee was not inſeriour to the very chieſe Apoſtles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.5.</note> had yet the remnants of the old man. Now then it is no more I that doe it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.17.24.</note> 
               <hi>but the ſinne that dwelleth in me: O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from the bodie of this death?</hi> Therefore they may partlie ſtriue againſt their owne iudgment, and be drawne by temptation to defende an errour againſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; for howſoeuer errour in iudgement, commeth from ignorance: yet errour in act,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:18377:34"/>as in teaching, defending, and maintaing of ſome vntruth, is ioyned often with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; and ariſeth not out of ignorance, but out of want of grace, and ſanctification.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, becauſe that promiſe of the inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant aſſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; infallible guida<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the ſpirit, was neuer made to any ſaue to the Apoſtles becauſe they were to plant Churches, where were neuer any before; and being in a new ſorme of gouernment of the Church, which was neuer vſed nor heard of before, therefore to them it was promiſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 14.26.</note> 
               <hi>He ſhall teach y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> all things, and bring all things to your remembrance:</hi> and againe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.13.</note> 
               <hi>Hee ſhall lead you into all truth.</hi> By which is meant, not an abſolute illuminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all truth; for that the Apoſtle had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied before,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.9.</note> 
               <hi>Wee know in part:</hi> But an infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſuggeſtion of the truth, as occaſion was offered. And that this was promiſed onely to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I proue, becauſe of that, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.13. <hi>And he ſhall ſhew you all things to come;</hi> which neuer any Pope or Patriarch durſt challenge: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing they are both in one graunt, and that this will not paſſe by vertue of that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; then why the other, ſeeing they are both in one and the ſame promiſe?</p>
            <p>Now this being ſo certaine a truth, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> it will firſt euince the doctrine of poperie, of errour, which teacheth, that the Church cannot erre: nor a councell, which is the repreſentatiue Church; for when all Miniſters or the greater
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:18377:34"/>part may fall into groſſe errours, and things in a councell are caried by the moſt voyces, ſhall we thinke they may not then erre? for ſuppoſe a councell be collected of them, is it not likely they will be the ſame in the councell when they meete together, that they are, ſeuered, &amp; alone? for <hi>Coelum non animum mutat, &amp;c.</hi> They may well change the heauens and their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but not their minds and affections. But to inſtance in ſome, ſee a councel erring, 1. <hi>Kings.</hi> 22; 400. falſe prophets with one conſent adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing king <hi>Ahab.</hi> flat againſt the minde of God, and the word of the Lord, by the prophet <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaiah.</hi> But happely <hi>Bellarmine</hi> will ſay, they were a councell of prophets, not prieſts; gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the King, not by the high prieſt. See therefore councels of prieſts gathered by the high prieſt, and yet erring;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 9.22</note> In <hi>Iohn</hi> we haue a councell, which met and decreed to excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate whoſoeuer profeſſed Chriſt: did they not erre? And in <hi>Marke,</hi> there is a cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell which condemned Chriſt of blaſphemie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark.</hi> 14.64.</note> and that he ought to die for it: Thinke you they were in the truth, or in impious errour? But <hi>Bellarmine</hi> will ſay, that a councell of prieſts could not erre before Chriſts comming; but he being come, they might erre: but for what reaſon? muſt it not be, becauſe they were not prieſts, and their high prieſt no high prieſt, ſeeing Chriſt was now come? But this is falſe: for the prieſthood of <hi>Aaron</hi> was not aboliſhed, till
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:18377:35"/>Chriſt offered vp his ſacrifice, and ſo had eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed an cuerlaſting prieſthood: yea further, the argument of the Rhemiſts, which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to them, and other popiſh writers, how ſhould it hold good? when <hi>Iohn.</hi> 11.49.50. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Caiaphas</hi> ſpake the truth, they would prone the Pope could not erre, be he neuer ſo wicked: for if he were not a high prieſt, then there would be no conſequent in this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But he was the high prieſt, and they all prieſts, and yet they erred: and ſo a councell may erre. But more ingeniouſly dealeth <hi>Hoſius</hi> &amp; <hi>Canus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſius in lib. <hi>2.</hi> Corara Brentium. Prolegom. Canus lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. vlt. in reſponſ. ad Secund. argum. In action. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> who affirme directly, that that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell did pronounce a right ſentence, and that the ſpirit of God was with them, and that it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer left the councell of prieſts, till Chriſt had offered vp his bloudie ſacrifice: yet that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell condemned Chriſt of blaſphemie: and is not this the mouth of blaſphemie, that dare ſpeake ſuch things? But ſee other councels: the councell of <hi>Calcedon.</hi> not demed to be a lawfull councell, equalled the Biſhip of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> with the B B. of <hi>Rome,</hi> in authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, honour, and other priuiledges; ſaue onely in precedence.<note place="margin">Canon. <hi>19.</hi> de baeret. rebaptiz.</note> I hope they will ſay, this coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell erred. The firſt councell of <hi>Necce</hi> eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed rebaptization, of thoſe heritiques who ſollowed <hi>Sameſatenus.</hi> The ſecond councell of <hi>Neece,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Action. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> eſtabliſhed worſhipping of Images, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed that Angells had bodies, and that the ſoules of men were corporal. If a councell can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:18377:35"/>erre,<note place="margin">Auguſt. de baptiſm. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> why did <hi>Auguſtine</hi> appeale from the <hi>Affrican</hi> councel, where <hi>Cyprian</hi> was preſent, to the Scriptures? Affirming that we may not doubt of the Scriptures: but of them it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to doubt; ſaying, that <hi>Concilta plenaria,</hi> full councels may erre. If the queſtion be of the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the pope, whether it be greater then of a councell, <hi>Hterome</hi> anſwereth; <hi>Si authoritas quaritur, or his maior eſt vrbe.</hi> If you queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> about ſuperiority, the whole world is aboue one city. But aske the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel of <hi>Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</hi> which depoſed <hi>Iohn</hi> 23. &amp; choſe <hi>Martin.</hi> 5. If they ſay the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell erred, they grant as much as we deſire; If they ſay that the councell did not erre, then the authoritie of the councell is aboue the Pope. But why ſhould I contend ſo long about councels, ſeeing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues haue brought it to a narrower ſcantling? for they confeſſe that all particular Churches may erre, except the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> too,<note place="margin">Bellarm. de po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifice Rom. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi> Idem. lib. <hi>4.</hi> Cap. <hi>3.</hi> Bellarm. de pontif. Romano. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> if the Pope ſhould tranſlate his ſeate from <hi>Rome,</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> did from <hi>Antioch;</hi> and for coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, that all generall councels may erre, not confirmed by the Pope. So that if it be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that the pope, who is their virtual Church, can erre, then all is granted. And firſt before I ſhew you that they haue erred in particular, I will let you ſee the ſtrength of ſome of their Reaſons, whereby they would prooue he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not erre.<note place="margin">Luke. <hi>22.32.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bellarmine</hi> reaſoneth out of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of <hi>Luke,</hi> thus; <hi>I haue prayed for thee, that
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:18377:36"/>thy faith faile not.</hi> Here ſaith <hi>Bellarmine, Chriſt obtained</hi> 2. <hi>priuiledges for</hi> Peter: <hi>one, that he could neuer looſe true faith, though he were tempted of the diucll. Another that he, as he is high prieſt, could neuer teach any thing contraric to faith; or that in his ſeate neuer any ſhould be found which ſhould teach contraric to the true faith. The firſt of thoſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>perhaps doth not deſcend to the ſucceſſors of</hi> Peter. Very well then, by <hi>Bellarmines</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, the Pope perhaps may looſe true faith; nay I would for their owne ſakes it were but perhaps: and yet I thinke it is without all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps that he cannot; for a man cannot looſe that he neuer had. Popes, as Popes, neuer had true faith; For antichriſt cannot poſſibly haue it; then it is without perhaps he cannot looſe it, but this but by the way: but <hi>the latter,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is without all doubt deriued to them.</hi> Is it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and why I pray you? What reaſon can you giue that theſe words ſhould conuey two grauntes and priuiledges to <hi>Peter,</hi> and but one to his ſucceſſors? Doubtleſſe none is giue by him, neither can be giuen: but yet he will proue it: by what? As impudent &amp; ſhameleſſe as he is, to wreſt Scripture to his purpoſe, yet can he find none with any colour to offer this violence vnto. But do not the Fathers ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm. Though his <hi>Vſe</hi> be to make fathers ſpeak what he would haue them, yet they cannot be ſorced by him here; how then doth he proue it? only by certaine ſentences of ſeuen Popes,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:18377:36"/>and ſome ſewe late writers. But is it equall that parties ſhould be witneſſes or Iudges? or are we now without Scripture, or antiquity, to take any thing for truth which a few popes or ſome new writers ſhall affirme? at leaſt muſt we take them in ſo maine a matter, as this is? I take it, none can iuſtly reprooue vs if we reiect them, eſpecially when we haue ſo good reaſon out of the text, that it can carie no ſuch thing. And that I prooue thus; Becauſe that by faith here is not meant an hiſtoricall faith, or the ſaith of doctrine; but a iuſtifying faith, or the faith of the heart: not a generall faith, but a particular; not that by which we belecue God, but in God; which failes not by errour, ſo it be not ſundamentall: for ſo we ſhould haue condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned all whoſoeuer haue liued; but when a man doth fall wholly from grace, and ccaſeth to be a member of Chriſt. And that it is ſo, appeares, firſt from thoſe words, <hi>That thy faith ſhould not ſaile:</hi> not vaniſh away or be extinct as <hi>Chriſ.</hi> ſaith; which cannot be vnderſtood of any other ſaith, but of that by which we ſtand and are ſaued: for, the other faith may faile, not once, but often; and a man be ſaued notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. 2. From thoſe words, <hi>When thou art conuerted ſtrengthen thy brethren: that is,</hi> after thou haſt repented and art conuerted, ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then thy brethren, &amp; ſuſtaine their faith; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, their ſauing faith; of which they confeſſe ſome of theirs may be deſtitute. 3. Out of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:18377:37"/>the driſt and ſcope of our Sauiour Chriſt: for his drift was to arme and protect <hi>Peter,</hi> againſt that try all and temptation, that he then fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told him of: not againſt errour in teaching the Church, but againſt apoſtaſie in time of tryal; therefore faith <hi>Thcophilact, hee ſheweth him the particular temptation:</hi> for our Sauiour would not arme there where he was not to be hurt, where there was no daunger, nor put a helmet on the head, where the heart and breaſt was to be ſmitten. And thus much <hi>Bellarmine</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſeth, when he makes <hi>Peters</hi> fall to bee a matter of fact (to caſt vtterly off his former profeſſion) and not of ſaith, and therefore it was perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance in the habit of iuſtifying faith, not infallibilitie in the matter of his hiſtoricall faith that Chriſt prayed for: which ſo differs, that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may haue the one, that is, iuſtifying faith, and yet hold an crrour, not fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, to the death; as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> contends, for the Fathers diuerſe of them: and the other, that is, a right beliefe of the generall poynts of religion, and yet not haue iuſtifying faith, nor ſauing and ſanctiſiing grace; as <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> confeſſeth the Pope cannot erre, and yet profeſſeth he may want ſauing grace. 4. Pro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 31. verſe, where Chriſt affirmeth that he praved for other of the Apoſtles as well as <hi>Peter,</hi> ſeeing Satan oppoſed them, and ſought to winnow them as wel as <hi>Peter:</hi> Now for theſe Chriſt queſtionleſſe prayed, vnleſſe wee ſhall
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:18377:37"/>thinke that one was not as deere to him as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother: not <hi>Iohn</hi> the beloued, as <hi>Peter:</hi> nay he loued all with a very great loue, and ſo pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for them. 5. It is anſwered, that the thing he prayed for here, was a thing not proper to <hi>Peter,</hi> but common to all the Apoſtles, yea all the Elect; and if the gift and grace bee common to all, and the ſame perſon made the ſame prayer in effect for all, as hee doth, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 17.9; <hi>I pray for them which thou haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen me out of the world.</hi> And verſe 11. <hi>Holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther keepe them in thy name:</hi> &amp; verſe 20. <hi>I pray not for theſe alone, but them alſo which ſhall beleeue in me through their word:</hi> what can they make out of it for their particular? for by vertue of this prayer, not only not <hi>Pet.</hi> but none of the Apoſtles, yea none of the faithfull can fall from that faith there ſpoken of. Vpon which ground, the ancient Fathers apply this place to al the Apoſtles, yea all the elect: and if to al, then helpes it them but a little. The ſecond proofe, he cannot erre, is <hi>Math.</hi> 16.18. <hi>Thou art Peter, and vpon this rocke will I build my Church: and the gates of hell ſhall not ouercome it.</hi> Whence they firſt reaſon, that the foundation and rock of the Church cannot erre; ſuch as <hi>Peter</hi> and the Pope his ſucceſſors: I ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: it is not yet prooued that the Pope is <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſor; Nay, it is manifeſt that hee ſucceeded rather <hi>Symon Magus,</hi> then <hi>Symo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> But I ſay, that <hi>Peter</hi> is not the rock: In
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:18377:38"/>the words ſaith <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> there is a difference betweene <hi>Petra</hi> and <hi>Petrus,</hi> both in the Greek and Latine. Againe, the rock here meant, is not <hi>Peter</hi> but Chriſt; which is affirmed by Samt <hi>Paul,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>They dranke of the ſpirt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall rocke, that fall nved them; and that rocke was Chriſt:</hi> and <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. <hi>other foundation can no manlay then that which is laid, which is Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> wherevnto agree the Fathers, and their owne writers, and alſo late writers; whereby all colour of argument, taken from this place for the Pope, is vtterly quaſhed: but grant that they begge, then muſt it be either in regard of his perſon; but that cannot be, for the Church cannot bee built vpon fleſh and bloud: or in regarde of ſome ſuperioritie and place aboue the reſt, but as it cannot be proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, ſo the contrarie is manifeſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.11. <hi>For in nothing was I infer iour to the very chiefe Apoſtles:</hi> or of his doctrine taught by him, and of this faith of Chriſt confeſſed by him; ſo it is true: now this was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to him with al the reſt: for as <hi>Iohn</hi> is called a pillar, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.9. ſo was <hi>Iames</hi> as well as <hi>Peter,</hi> and all the reſt: as <hi>Reue.</hi> 21.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.14.</note> 
               <hi>The wall of the Citic had twelue foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, and in them the names of the lambes</hi> twelue Apoſtles, to which is that, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.20. Built vpon the foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.20.</note> with whom the Prophets are ioyned, becauſe they wrote the Scripture, which is indeede the ſoundation of our faith,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:18377:38"/>they being put for their writings; but of all this, nothing will followe for the Pope, or nothing in eſpeciall manner. Now that you haue ſeene the ſtrength of ſome of his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, by which you may coniecture of the reſt, I will ſhew you how this chalenge of the neuer erring Pope, is an impudent errour; by producing many of them, who haue erred, and leaue you to iudge of the reſt. I am not ignorant, that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> indeuours to excuſe all or moſt of theſe I ſhall produce: time will not permit to let you ſee at large how ſlender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he hath done it; yet a little will I ſhew you and leaue you to iudge the Oxe by his hoofe. The firſt ſhall bee <hi>Peter,</hi> whom though not prooued yet we will confeſſe that hee was B. of <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e:</hi> did he not apparantly <hi>deny Chriſt?</hi> was he not ignorant <hi>of the aboliſhing of the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall law,</hi> yea <hi>of the calling of the Gentries?</hi> Whom <hi>Bellarmine</hi> excuſeth for his deniall of Chriſt, that he was not then <hi>Summus Pontifex the high prieſt:</hi> and why not? becauſe Chriſt gaue him that in the twentieth of <hi>Iohn,</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>Paſce oues, feede my ſheepe:</hi> he hath gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned much by his anſwere; for if hee was not made chiefe prieſt till then, then was he not, when Chriſt ſaid to him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 16.18.</note> 
               <hi>Thou art Peter and vpon this rocke will I builde my Church:</hi> and <hi>I haue prayed for thee, that thy faith ſhould not faile:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.32.</note> which was ſpoken long before: and ſo hath he at one blow depriued himſelfe of two of the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:18377:39"/>ſtrongeſt arguments, he hath to prooue the Pope cannot erre. Ne ther can we admit of his ſhift, that theſe were promiſes, that Chriſt would make him in future time the foundatio of the Church, but not performances; for that wee haue the whole colledge of Ieſuites a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamſt this one: who vpon the place aſſirme, that Chriſt gaue <hi>Peter</hi> now to be the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>He doth not,</hi> ſay they, <hi>ſo much call him by the name</hi> Peter <hi>or Ro ke, as he doth affirme him to be a Rocke.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thomas in <hi>4.</hi> Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. diſt. <hi>4.9.</hi>
               </note> And <hi>T. Aquinas</hi> ſaith; that in theſe words, now firſt was giuen to <hi>Peter</hi> power ouer all the Apoſtles. And if theſe bee not weightie inough againſt him, becauſe his head is liſted aboue them, ſee one a ſtep at oue him.<note place="margin">Viſt. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> Pope <hi>Anacletus</hi> in his ſecond Epiſtle writeth, that to <hi>Peter</hi> firſt the prelateſhip was giuen, the Lord ſaying: <hi>Thouart Peter.</hi> Now I adde, that ſeeing <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and they all contend, that <hi>Peter</hi> is a rocke and foundation, and here Chriſt ſaith to him: thou art <hi>Peter,</hi> not thou ſhalt be <hi>Peter:</hi> hee here performeth, that he euer gaue him, and doth not barely promiſe. Finally, by the future-tenſe, is not nere noted a promiſe, but a perpetuall, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent, &amp; continuing to the time following: as the Hebrew Grammarians do note vnto vs. Again he anſwereth that that he did, was <hi>Ore,</hi> not <hi>Corde:</hi> as if we ſhould iudge an heretique by the thought of his heart, and not by the words of his mouth. That it was not with his
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:18377:39"/>heart, it ſerueth to extenuate, and make him more capable of remiſſion. but it ſerueth not to take away the offence. Now <hi>Bellarmine</hi> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth nothing touching the other two, of his ignorance of the aboliſhing of the ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all law, and the calling of the Gentiles; which errours he certainly had, after he was <hi>Summus Pontifex,</hi> if euer he were: for they were after the reſurrection of Chriſt; yea after his aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo after that, <hi>Feede my ſheepe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſhalbe <hi>Marcellinus, who offred vp Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to Idols,</hi> &amp; was made by the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel of <hi>Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa</hi> to recant it. For whom, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith, that he taught nothing againſt faith, neither was he an heretique nor infidell: but <hi>in the externall act, and for feare of death.</hi> But I anſwere, it is not likely, but that the ſame feare would haue made alſo his tongue to haue ſpoken as much if he had bene compelled to it, and to haue taught the ſame; &amp; for the excuſe that <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> makes, that he did it for feare; It is falſe:<note place="margin">Aadrad. lib. <hi>2.</hi> de defenſ. Trident. Concil.</note> For <hi>Andradius</hi> ſaith, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed in the <hi>Synneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan</hi> Councel, that he was corrupted with mony, <hi>Iudas</hi> like. Further it is falſe, which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith, that he taught not againſt faith: for he taught by deed, though not by word. Now <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> ſaith, <hi>Eſſicacius loquitur vox operis, quam ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monis,</hi> Deeds teach more effectually then words. And by this, <hi>Marcellinus</hi> drewe many to offer ſacrifices to Idols: yea and by it, did more hurt to the Church, then if he had taught by
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:18377:40"/>word. The third <hi>Liberius,</hi> who as <hi>Htecome</hi> and <hi>Athanaſius</hi> write of him,<note place="margin">Athanaſ. its epiſt. ad ſolitar. vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agentes.</note> 
               <hi>denyed the deitte of Chriſt.</hi> How excuſeth the <hi>Ieſuite</hi> him? for ſooth he was not an hereticke, but onely in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward act, and that not expreſly, but by impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; becauſe he condemned <hi>Athanaſius</hi> whome he knew to be perſecuted for the true ſaith. But <hi>Athanaſius</hi> cotradicts <hi>Bellarm.</hi> who hued at the ſame time, baniſhed for the ſame cauſe; who ſaith, that <hi>Liberius</hi> after he had li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued two yeares in haniſhment, relented, and by the treatning of death was brought to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, namely to <hi>the Arrtan hereſie.</hi> But to adde no more teſtimonie, I would knowe of <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> if <hi>Liberius</hi> were not an herticke, how <hi>Foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix</hi> the ſecond could be Pope, and the Church honour him and worihip him, as Pope; euen while <hi>Liberius</hi> was aline? and the <hi>Romane</hi> Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie choſe him Pope as he conſeſſeth. The fourth ſhal be <hi>Foelix. Liberius</hi> his ſucceſſor, an <hi>Arrian</hi> alſo, as <hi>Ierom</hi> writeth. For him, whereas <hi>Hierom</hi> ſaith he was an <hi>Arria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Pope, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith, that that word <hi>Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> was thruſt into the text; or if not ſo, that he was an <hi>Arrian</hi> onely when he was not true Pope, being choſen before by the <hi>Arrian</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and not by the <hi>Romane</hi> Cleargie. Becauſe faith he, <hi>Liberius</hi> was not yet depriued: but ſome two yeares after, when as <hi>Liberius</hi> fel into his hereſie, the <hi>Roman</hi> Cleargie depoſed him, &amp; choſe the other: not that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> alloweth
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:18377:40"/>the Cleargie, in that action; howſoeuer he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends that he was no heretike. As for <hi>Felix, Bellarmine</hi> confeſſeth, that he communicated with the <hi>Arrians,</hi> that they choſe him Biſhop: which is a great argument that he was an <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian;</hi> And if he was not then right and true Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, then was the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> not onely without her owne Biſhop, he being ſent into baniſhment, but without any Biſhop at all; and that for two yeares ſpace: which how it will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage them to grant, let them looke to it. The fiſt <hi>Siricius,</hi> who held, that <hi>matrimonie was vncleanneſſe, and pollution of the fleſh,</hi> which God had made honorable. Touching whom, <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Caluine</hi> after his manner, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently lyeth, for that <hi>Siricius</hi> ſpake not of lawfull mariage, but vnlawfull coniunction. But he that giues the lie, hath more right to keepe it to himſelfe; and in this very thing, for whoſoeuer ſhall read his Epiſtle the 5. and 7. chapters, ſhall find no ſuch thing: for he commandeth ſingle life to prieſts, and calleth their mariage pollution, and wickedly for his purpoſe (which is that, <hi>Caluine</hi> reprooueth) abuſeth the words of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> ſaying;<note place="margin">Sirius in Epiſt. ad Hiſpan. cap. <hi>5.</hi> &amp; <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>And they who are in the fleſh (witneſſe the elect veſſell) cannot pleaſe God; but you are not in the fleſh, but in the ſpirit, if ſo be the ſpirit of God dwell in you. And where can the ſpirit of God dwell, but</hi> (as we read) <hi>in holy bodies?</hi> Doth not this apparantly ſhew,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:18377:41"/>that he accounted marriage vncleanneſſe, and pollution?</p>
            <p>In the ſixt place, <hi>Vigilius;</hi> who curſed them that held <hi>that Chriſt had two natures.</hi> Which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> cannot deny, but plainly confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, that he writ ſuch an impious Epiſtle, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy the name of a Chriſtian, wherein he condemned all who affirmed <hi>Chriſt to haue two natures.</hi> But ſaith he, he did not defend any thing publikely; neither was an heretike in hart, but ſecretly in a priuate Epiſtle, which he did for deſire of authoritie. Againe, that he did, was then when he was not truly and lawfully Biſhop; for <hi>Syluerius</hi> was yet liuing, who was Pope, though in baniſhment. To the firſt I aunſwere, Whether it was publiquelie or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately, it is not to the matter; he did it and hereſie priuate, I hope, is hereſie; whether it was in the heart or no, that was knowne to God: and wee may iudge truly of his heart by his writings. If theſe ſhifts would ſcrue, no body ſhould euer be knowne or determined to be an heretike. To the ſecond, I anſwere; that <hi>Liberatus</hi> his words,<note place="margin">Liberat. in brcuia. cap. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> in the end of the chap. are theſe; <hi>Vigilius writting theſe things cloſely to the heritikes, permanſit ſedens,</hi> did ſtill keepe his ſeate; namely, after the death of <hi>Syluerius,</hi> who dyed as <hi>Sigebertus</hi> writeth, the ſame yeare he was baniſhed.</p>
            <p n="7">7 <hi>Honorius</hi> the firſt, who denied that <hi>Chriſt
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:18377:41"/>had two wils, &amp; two operations;</hi> as <hi>Melchior Canus</hi> and diuers other Popes and councells haue written. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> would gladly anſwere, that thoſe epiſtles of <hi>Honorius</hi> were fained, &amp; falſely imputed to him: but, that hee will not greatly ſtand too; but tells vs in the ſecond place, that <hi>Honourius</hi> did holde no ſuch thing, in thoſe Epiſtles, but onely forbids the vſing of the words of one or two wils, and operations. And being preſſed with it, that in thoſe Epiſtles, he hath theſe very words; <hi>Vnam voluntatem fate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur domini Wee confeſſe one will of the Lord:</hi> hee anſwereth, that hee ſpeaketh there of his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine nature, onely; and would ſay that in the man Chriſt, there were not 2. contrary willes, one of the fleſh, another of the ſpirit; but one onely of the ſpirit. I aunſwere, that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he would haue ſaid, it's apparant what hee did ſay; it may be <hi>Bellarmine</hi> would hee had ſaid thus: but the wordes are plaine; and not to vs onely who may be thought parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, but to 3. <hi>Synodes,</hi> as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> confeſſeth, and to 2. or 3. Popes. Now Iudge whether it be equall that we ſhould beleeue <hi>Bellarm.</hi> before ſo many Fathers, and ſuch authoritie; as if he had better vnderſtood him, then all they did.<note place="margin">Auguſt. cont. Iul. Pelag. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi> &amp; al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8 So <hi>Innocent</hi> the firſt, holding that <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme and the Euchariſt, was neceſſary for chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to ſaluation,</hi> as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writeth the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whereof was conſuted by the councell of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:18377:42"/>
               <hi>Trent,</hi> 5. Seſſion vnder <hi>Pius</hi> 4. whom <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> ſeekes to defend from other errours, and hereſies, and not from theſe; paſſing them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in ſilence: and ſo we take him for conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to our accuſation of him; for, that he held ſuch things, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> could not be ignorant, ſeeing <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh of them in many places.</p>
            <p n="9">9 Behold <hi>Stephen</hi> the 6. aboliſhing <hi>all the Acts of Formoſus</hi> his predeceſſor, <hi>and decreeing that</hi> the <hi>Sacrament depended vpon the vertue of the Prteſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10 After him commeth <hi>Iohn</hi> the ninth, who <hi>diſannulled all the</hi> Acts of <hi>Stephen, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed whatſoeuer Formoſus had done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the 11. place, <hi>Sergins</hi> the third <hi>diſannulled whatſoeuer Formoſus and Iohn had done, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhed the Acts of Stephen.</hi> It may well be, that all theſe may be in an errour: but ſure it is, they all could not be in the truth.</p>
            <p>For the defence or excuſe of theſe three, hee ſaith, that touching <hi>Formoſus,</hi> the queſtion was, whether <hi>Formoſus</hi> was true and lawfull Pope: <hi>Stephen</hi> thought bee was not. <hi>Iohn</hi> the ninth, after, round the contrarie, and condemned the Acts of <hi>Stephen.</hi> As if the holy Ghoſt did erre more in iudging of a fact, then in iudging of the right: he is God and knoweth all things. They ſay the ſpirit of God is giuen to their Church, and as it were
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:18377:42"/>tyed to their Councels, being ouer them, to lead them into all truth: But to condemne him, that was not to be condemned, is farre from the truth, and cannot come from the ſpirit of God. But he ſaith, <hi>Iohn</hi> ſound out that which <hi>Stephen</hi> did not, that <hi>Formoſus</hi> was a true Pope: by what meanes did hee finde it? ſure by the ſpirit of God: and could the ſpirit finde it out in the councell of <hi>Raucnna,</hi> vnder <hi>Iohn</hi> the ninth, and not finde it in the councell of <hi>Rome,</hi> vnder <hi>Stephen</hi> the 6? Nay not only not find it out, but iudge the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? Are then the iudgements of the ſpirit of God contrary one to another? But graunt <hi>Iohn</hi> did finde out things thus, was this then the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of the holy Ghoſt? By what ſpirit then did <hi>Sergius</hi> the third, ſucceeding <hi>Iohn.</hi> condemne <hi>Formoſus</hi> againe, and abrogate all his acts and take him the ſecond time out of the graue, and cut off his head, and caſt his boly into <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber?</hi> which being found by fiſhermen, was brought into the cathedral Churche at <hi>Rome,</hi> where the Images did worſhip him, beleeue it if you will. What probabilitie and truth is like to be in theſe excuſes, you may eaſily coniec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. To make vp the dozen, See <hi>Iohn</hi> 22. cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led as ſome ſay the 21. who if he denied not the <hi>immortalitie of the ſoule as Caluine</hi> affirmes, and <hi>Bellarmine</hi> denies; yet held he, that <hi>the ſoules departed, neuer came into the preſence of God till
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:18377:43"/>the reſurrectio of the body.</hi> Which errour the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie of <hi>Paris</hi> oppoſing; by the helpe of <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> they made him recant with the ſound of a Trumpet, for feare of loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his Popedome, as <hi>Iohn Gerſon</hi> affirmes in his Sermon of Eaſter. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> excuſeth him, that though he held ſuch an opinion, yet he might do it without danger of hereſie: for the Church had not yet defined it to be an errour; a very ſriuolous excuſe. For it there had not bene, before, any definition of the Church, (which he falſely affirmeth) yet had we the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition of the Lord, in the Scripture; which he hath appointed to be the rule of faith to his Church, and not the Church to be a rule to others. She may declare ſomething to be an hereſie, but her determination cannot make it an hereſie: and if ſhe had neuer defined it to be an hereſie: yet had it beene an errour; and hee had therein manifeſtly erred, who either then or now ſhall holde it.</p>
            <p n="13">13 To giue you the aduantage, ſee <hi>Iohn</hi> the 23. who denied both <hi>Eternall life and the reſurection of the body.</hi> Concerning whom, Firſt, the Ieſuite ſaith it is vncertaine, whether he were true Pope, becauſe there was at that time two Popes more; <hi>Gregorie</hi> the 12 and <hi>Benedict,</hi> the 13. each curſing other: ſo that if he erred, it is nothing to the erring of the Pope; becauſe it was not knowne who was
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:18377:43"/>Pope. Obſerue a monſtrous body, with three heads, or a body with no head; but his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe is but a ſhift: for <hi>Platina</hi> (who maketh him, <hi>Iohn</hi> the 24.) affirmeth, that he was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Pope at <hi>Bononia,</hi> with the conſent of all:<note place="margin">Platina in Iohn <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> but ſecondly, he anſwereth that at the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> 53. Articles were put vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and prooued by ſubſtantiall wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and thoſe were all for matter of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; but as for this and ſome other Articles of faith, they were prooued by no witneſſes: therefore ſaith he, it is probable, that by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his vitious life, the opinion of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple was, that he thought there was neither life euerlaſting, nor the reſurection of the body. So by excuſing of him from errour, he hath ſtemed him, and made him ſtinke in the noſthrils of all honeſt men: And if the head was ſo bad, all the body was worſe. But the councell obiecting it to him, and hee not cleering himſelfe of it, nay his life gaue teſtimonie of it, why ſhould we beleeue <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> before all the Fathers of that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel? But leauing theſe things, I haſten towards an end, and come to apply this, for our more particular benefite.</p>
            <p>This then may teach euery man, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> ſeeing things ſtand thus, to labour for the knowledge of the word, and the myſteries of Saluation; that hauing the rule of truth, he may be able
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:18377:44"/>to iudge of all falſehood, and errour, and may not be caried away with the errour of one or many, be they neuer ſo great or learned. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it is, that becauſe they know but in part, they may erre though they be neuer ſo lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and erre often times they do, becauſe they are not wholly ſanctified. It is certaine that the greateſt part of a viſible Church is euer vnſanctified: and the beſt part that is ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, is but ſanctified in part, and ſo ſubiect to partialitie and errour; and may both erre, and defend errour againſt their knowledge; ſome violent temptation, of pride, pleaſure, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, carrying them therto. Seeing none are now gouerned by the infallible guidance of the ſpirit of God; then had men need of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that they may be able to trie the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines that are deliuered. It is a certaine truth, and not to be denyed, becauſe ſtories of all times do manifeſtly prooue it; that errour, and herefie, haue oftentimes ſo much preuailed, that they who haue holden and poſſeſſed the places of office, and dignitie in the Church of God, either for feare, ſlatterie, hope of gaine, and honour, or miſled by their owne igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and ſimplicitie, or fallen into ſome er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, giuen ouer of God, haue departed from the ſoundnes of Faith: ſo that the ſinceritie of religion was vpholden, and the truth defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and maintained, only by ſome fewe, that
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:18377:44"/>were moleſted, perſecuted, tra luced as turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and ſeditious perſons, and enimies to the common peace of the Chriſtian world. This were eaſie to be ſhewed in the times of Chriſt, and of the immediate ſucceſſors, the Apoſtles. This was manifeſt in the times of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> when in the councel of <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leuci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and <hi>Arminium,</hi> the <hi>Nicene</hi> Faith was condemned, and all the B B. of the whole world ſell from the ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the Faith, ſaue <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and a ſewe confeſſors that were baniſhed with him; So as <hi>Ierom</hi> writes againſt the <hi>Luciſerians</hi> ſaying, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gemuit totus orbis &amp; miratus eſt, ſe faclum eſſe drianum.</hi> The whole world groned, and is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed to ſee how ſhe was become an <hi>Arrian.</hi> So <hi>Hillarius,</hi> againſt <hi>Auxentius</hi> Biſhop of Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan, complaineth, that the <hi>Arrian</hi> faction had confounded all; and therefore, admoniſhed men to take heed how they were led by any outward appearance or glorious ſhewes. Now as there is no new thing vnder the heauens; but that that is now, hath bene before: ſo there is no old thing, but it may be renewed, and ſuch times may befall the Church againe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is the wiſedome of euery man that is not careleſſe which end goeth forward,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.1.</note> and retchleſſe of his ſoules health, to labour for knowledge, that he may be able as S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>to trie the Spirits; for many falſe prophets are gone out into the world.</hi> If any man will ſay, how ſhall
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:18377:45"/>not we erre, when ſo many great learued men haue erred and may erre? The anſwere is, as <hi>Salmon</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 28.11.</note> 
               <hi>The rich man is wiſe in his owne conceit; but the poore that hath vnderſtanding can trie him:</hi> So, oftentimes meaner men may found the depth, and ſee more then great ſchollers; eſpecially, ſeeing that he that was truth hath ſaid it; <hi>God reucaleth that to ſuckelings and babes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 11.25.</note> 
               <hi>that he hideth from wiſe and prudent.</hi> Let vs then account of that doctrine of pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as damnable, which commendeth an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit faith, and be ſuſpicious of thoſe who thinke it is not good for men to haue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; as if they mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t either to make a pray vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, or to broach ſome groſſe errours, and therefore deale with them as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith, Theeues do; <hi>Firſt put out the candle, and then fall a ſpoyling:</hi> and as deceitfull Marchants, that would vtter their wares by obſcure and deceitfull lights. And let vs againe labour for knowledge, that we may be able to trie the ſpirits, &amp; not be deceiued, by any ſeducers; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, when it will not goe for currant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, that we haue beene ſo taught and miſled, by our guides: for <hi>if the blind lead the blind, they ſhall both fall into the ditch</hi> and bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured together. Which that we may eſcape, let vs follow men, though they be Apoſtles, no further then they follow Chriſt. And that we may be able to diſcerne others ſteppes, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:18377:45"/>they tread right or no; Let vs imbrace the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> exhortation, or commaund;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cot.</hi> 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>Let the word of Chriſt dwell plentifully in vs.</hi> By which, we may be preſerued from error; being the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all antidote againſt this poyſon: yea and aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in it, we ſhall walke in the truth,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.23.</note> and in the end be ſaued, by the truth. <hi>Now the God of peace</hi> and truth, <hi>ſanctifie you, throughout: and I pray God that your whole ſpirit and ſoule and bodie may be kept blameleſſe, vnto the Comming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:18377:46"/>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by T. C. For Edmond Weauer, and William Welby. 1609.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18377:46"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
